<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise against irreligion. By H.C. de Luzancy, priest of the Church of England, and M. of Arts of Christs Church in Oxford</title>
            <author>De Luzancy, H. C. (Hippolyte du Chastelet), d. 1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 101 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36736</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2423B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201393</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825132</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825132</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29506</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36736)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29506)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1946:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise against irreligion. By H.C. de Luzancy, priest of the Church of England, and M. of Arts of Christs Church in Oxford</title>
                  <author>De Luzancy, H. C. (Hippolyte du Chastelet), d. 1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 32, 25-167 [i.e. 181], [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for E.W. and are to be sold by Hen. Bonwicke, at the Red Lion in St. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a preliminary license leaf and a final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>P. 181 misnumbered 167; text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Irreligion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29506:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE Againſt Irreligion. By <hi>H. C. de Luzancy,</hi> Prieſt of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>M. of Arts</hi> of Chriſts Church in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>E. W.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Hen. Bonwicke,</hi> at the Red Lion in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1678.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29506:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29506:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:29506:3"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Guil. Jane.</signed>
               <date>January, 29. 1677.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29506:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>John</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Oxford,</hi> Dean of <hi>Chriſt-Church.</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Treatiſe againſt <hi>Irreligion,</hi> cannot be better directed then to your Lordſhip; whoſe life is one of the beſt proofs we have for Religion; whence we may not only conclude the truth of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, but alſo that its ſeverest rules are eaſy and practicable. Irreligious men may elude the clearest demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strations, and <hi>laugh them to ſcorn;</hi> but they cannot but wonder at, and yeild up themſelves to thoſe great examples which appear in your Lordſhips conduct. They strike at their hearts with an irreſistible force, and do not only convince them of, but alſo perſwade them to a better belief.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29506:4"/>
            <p>My Lord, your Lordſhip's both publick and private, Epiſcopal and Domestick vertues, make Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion aſham'd of its own principles, and do abundantly evince, that the <hi>Church of England,</hi> in theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter ages, wherein vices ſeem to have over-run the whole world, has still the means and vertues of the primitive time.</p>
            <p>Your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> refus'd the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est dignities in the Church, with as much earnestneſs as others court and follow them. Epiſcopacy, which uſually lays open thoſe defects, a private life had before happily conceal'd, did reveal in you all the qualities the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and the ancient Canons require in a Biſhop: you have taken upon you all the burden, and left all the Splendor of ſo great a charge; and your Lordſhip rather ſuffers then enjoys the honours that are inſeparable from it.</p>
            <p>You give the Clergy of your Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, the example of a penitent and laborious life, of a constant ſelf
<pb facs="tcp:29506:4"/>denial of an indefatigable chartiy, of an even and unblamable conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, of unſpeakable love to the ancient ſpirit of the Church, and of an uninterrupted reſidency and care of their Flocks; they verify in your Lordſhip, that famous ſaying of one of the greatest Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops that ever was. <hi>Verus Amor recti habet in ſe Apoſtolorum Conſilia, &amp; Apoſtolicas Sanctio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lord,</hi> I had the happineſs to be for two years together wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your Lordſhips holy life; when I was under your govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Chriſts Church,</hi> that mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent Colledg. <hi>Which the gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur of its buildings, and ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of its revenues commend leſs then the gravity of its Canons, and the number, learning, vertue, and civility of its Students.</hi> The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> who know no equal out of this Kingdom, and is now, and has been for many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years together a ſeminary of great men both in Church and State;
<pb facs="tcp:29506:5"/>owes to your Lorſhip the greatest part of her ſplendor, you improve her buildings, increaſe her reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues; enlarge her libraries; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage all arts and ſcience to flock to her as to their center, keep up the strictneſs of her diſcipline, and the reverence due to her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees.</p>
            <p>I receiv'd there ſo many favours of your Lordſhip's, both in publick and private for the comfort of my ſoul, and the improvement of my studies, that I ſhould be guilty of a most notorious ingratitude; if I did not let the World know how good and generous your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip has been to me. This is the end, my Lord of this Dedication; and I will think my weak endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours abundantly rewarded, if I can perſwade the World that you have engag'd me to be as long as I live,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt humble and moſt obedient Servant;</hi> H. C. de Luzancy.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:29506:5"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THE Reader muſt expect here no demonſtrations for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion. This Treatiſe which is rather an eſſay then a book, ſuppoſes it not as demonſtrated, but only as probable as Irreligion ſeems to be to Irreligious Men. And that this may not ſeem to be ſaid at a venture, it is prov'd firſt, that Irreligion cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrated; But has only in the minds of its votaries a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of probability: ſo that Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Religion, are equally probable. And 2ly, that ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Christianity as probable, it is the greatest madneſs in the World not to embrace it.</p>
            <p>This is the deſign of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, of which it may be ſaid, that the form is new, or at least ſeems to be manag'd after ſuch a manner, as to leave no room to the ſlanderers of Christianity, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices to its adverſaries.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:29506:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29506:6"/>
            <head>A TREATISE Againſt Irreligion: The Firſt Diſcourſe.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The eaſieſt way to bring an Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious man to believe, is to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his doubts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are a ſort of men ſo affected concerning Chriſtian Religion, as neither to reject it as totally falſe, nor embrace it as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:29506:7"/>true; but they hang between both, mov'd by the different impreſſions that Faith on the one ſide, and the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Irreligion on the other, work in their minds. They owe to that confus'd mixture of opinions, that they are neither wholly Religious nor Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. They perform the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward offices of Religion, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill of what it propoſes to believe, to hope, and to fear; and leaving to their fate to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide what ſhall become of them after their death, they only mind now an eaſie and contented life.</p>
               <p>Some have gone further; and doubting has ſo far prevail'd upon them, as to choak and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:29506:7"/>extinguiſh in them the very leaſt ſpark of Faith. Either they own no other Divinity but Nature, as the <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of a God, they deny Chriſt, as the <hi>Deiſts,</hi> and hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the World to be eternal, and the Soul mortal, cut off the conſequences attending the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality of the Soul, <hi>viz.</hi> the laſt Judgment, Heaven, and Hell.</p>
               <p>How different ſoever theſe two ſorts of men appear to us, yet it may be ſaid that their Errors flow from the ſame ſource, <hi>viz.</hi> an uncertainty and inſtability of mind, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acts reaſons for every thing, and being ſatisfi'd with none, ſticks cloſe to the poſſeſſion of its
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29506:8"/>freedom. All the difference between them is, that the one carry their doubts ſo far as to become raſhly confident, and miſtake that for falſhood which is not demonſtrated, as they are pleas'd to fancy it; whereas the others ſtill doubting, ſtill ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſolute, bring themſelves to a neutrality not a whit better than an open and profeſs'd impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>It is very often needleſs to make uſe of ſolid reaſons to cure them whom their preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices arm and fence againſt all reaſons. They reject Scripture, laugh at Tradition, ſuſpect whatſoever is beyond the reach of a natural underſtanding, tho it be never ſo little; and ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29506:8"/>Faith of all the Authority it has over us, admit of no other principles but Reaſon, Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and the Teſtimony of their Senſes.</p>
               <p>And ſo the ſtrongeſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that Religion claims, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move or oppoſe Errours, being drawn from Scripture and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, rejecting either of them, they think themſelves invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible, becauſe they ſhift till they cannot be ſpoken or fought withal.</p>
               <p>It may be ſo far condeſcended with them, as to make uſe of nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; nay, as to lay aſide all the proofs Hiſtory, Philoſophy and Nature affords, and only ſtick to their doubts and uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:29506:9"/>
               <p>I ſay doubts and uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; for if they have no demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration for Chriſtian Religion, they have none againſt it. The moſt learned in the myſteries of Irreligion, have not yet demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated the Eternity of the World, the Mortality of the Soul, the Impoſſibility of a Judgment, and of an eternally happy or unhappy Life. All that they have done is to elude and evade the Arguments brought to aſſert them; all which ſumm'd up, amounts at moſt to a probable doubt, but can never reach to a full and real perſwaſion.</p>
               <p>But the nature of doubt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be equal on both ſides, they muſt give us leave to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29506:9"/>doubt of the Dogmes of Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as of things that may be falſe. Nor can they complain we require too much of them, when we deſire them to aſſent, That <hi>it may be there is God; it may be our Soul is immortal; it may be the World had a beginning, and muſt have an end; it may be there is a Life to come.</hi> The Authority of ſo many Nations that ador'd God for five thouſand years, and Chriſt near two thouſand, is enough to counterballance their reaſons, and make the queſtion at leaſt dubious and uncertain; and is ſo far from doing them any wrong, that their condition cannot be more advantageous than to ſuppoſe their doubts, and look upon them as prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29506:10"/>that muſt end the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP II. <hi>That in things that are doubtful, 'tis an infallible Rule of Prudence, To cloſe with that Party where there is nothing to loſe, and much to gain. Application of that Rule to Chriſtianity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SElf-intereſt is the part man is moſt tender of: all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal conſiderations may move, but that only can perſwade and determine him to any thing; and ſince the time ſin brought him to take himſelf for his ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate end, he loves nothing but
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29506:10"/>himſelf, or if he loves any thing beſides, 'tis ſtill for himſelf, and the advantages he hopes from it. The greater they are, and the nearer they come to him, the more he is affected with them. Thus, tho friends, riches, and all other external advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſway extreamly with him; yet their influence comes ſhort of that which his liberty, health, life, reputation, and generally all thoſe, wherein his happineſs is concern'd, have upon him. So that if ſuch advantage is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes, as not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns him for a while, or for a part of himſelf, but embraces whatſoever his body and ſoul can compaſs through the ſpace of his eternity, there is no
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29506:11"/>doubt he will earneſtly run to it. If in things of leſs impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, as are his friends, his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, or his life, he ſeems ſo concern'd; what muſt not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from him, when he is ſenſible, that from what is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to him depends his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal happineſs or miſery?</p>
               <p>Upon that principle which no man can deny that has not diveſted nature, it is eaſie to raiſe another.</p>
               <p>In the choice of Opinions, the truth and falſhood whereof can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be certainly known, that Party is to be preferr'd, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you venture nothing if it be falſe, and win much if it be true; and that rejected where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in nothing is to be got,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29506:11"/>if it be true, and the loſs irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable, if it ſhould prove falſe.</p>
               <p>There is no wiſe man but aſſents to this maxim. Thus men order their undertakings, and not truſting the event of things, or their own meaſures which often miſcarry, they work upon that which is more certain to them. Thus, of two Remedies that are to be try'd, that is never apply'd which muſt kill the Patient if it does not cure him, but rather that which if it reſtores him not to his firſt ſtrength, will at leaſt prove harmleſs. Thus there is no Merchant but would engage in a Commerce, which if ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful, there is much to be got, if not, nothing to be loſt; and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29506:12"/>he that ſhould leave ſuch a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain for another, which if at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with all imaginable proſperity, there is nothing to be got, and if not, there is an inconceivable loſs to be ſuffer'd, would be lookt upon as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witcht and befool'd.</p>
               <p>Now let Chriſtianity and Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religion be try'd by this Rule, ſince both are a ſort of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, which every body is to meaſure by the riſque he runs, or the reward he hopes.</p>
               <p>Laying aſide all the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar reaſons that evince the truth and excellency of Chriſtianity, let this ſuffice, that it is certain that following it, if it proves true, there is eternal happineſs to be expected, and nothing is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29506:12"/>ventur'd if it proves falſe. Whereas the contrary is to be ſaid of Irreligion.</p>
               <p>The firſt part of this Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſo notorious, and ſo pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, that it ſeems needleſs to prove it. So that there remains but the ſecond to be made out, that ſuppoſing Chriſtianity proves falſe, we venture no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:29506:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>That ſuppoſing Chriſtianity proves falſe, we venture nothing at all.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALL the loſs Chriſtianity expoſes us to, is that of the inordinate pleaſures and ſenſualities of this life, which he that has been made a Diſciple of Chriſt at his Baptiſm, has promis'd to renounce. The Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious man can find no other riſque but this; and all he can ſay is, that a Chriſtian is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd by his condition to deny himſelf, and forſake the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil.</p>
               <p>But to unvail and cure this miſtake, let us compare as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29506:13"/>as we can the Irreligious man and the Chriſtian, both in their deaths, and in their lives, and it will eaſily be ſeen who of them ventures moſt.</p>
               <p>There is no other time wherein they may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd; for after their death, both in the opinion of the Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, are annihilated: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that two annihilated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings cannot be compar'd, the non-being putting them in the ſame rank, it were impoſſible to judge of the difference of their lives by a ſtate which makes them equal after their death.</p>
               <p>If then we look upon an Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious man, and a Chriſtian, when they are a-dying, we ſhall find them both ſo even con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29506:14"/>pleaſures or riches, and generally all that has paſt, that the one cannot claim the leaſt advantage over the other. I ſuppoſe that each of them liv'd a whole Age, with that diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that the firſt enjoy'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any interruption, and to the higheſt degree, all the pleaſures a long and happy life can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford; and the ſecond was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of all the delights the Law he obſerves prohibit to its Votaries. Nay, which is more, I ſuppoſe that he barr'd himſelf even from thoſe that are permitted, and ſtudied nothing all his life, but to hate and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie himſelf. Yet after all, it muſt be ſaid, that how vaſt a difference ſoever be ſeen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29506:14"/>them whilſt they live, they are perfectly even when they dye. The pleaſures of the Irreligious, and the ſufferings of the Chriſtian are equally gone. The voluptuous life of the firſt does not make him more happy; nor to have liv'd in torments a hundred years ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the ſecond more miſerable; the happineſs or miſery of the Soul conſiſting in what ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents now, and not in what ſhe reſented before.</p>
               <p>If remembrance contributes any thing to our preſent happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or miſery, the Irreligious are certainly moſt miſerable. Death is his miſery, and the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the Chriſtian. It ends the pleaſures of the firſt and the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29506:15"/>ſufferings of the ſecond. It is the comfort of them that pine away their lives in torment, and the deſpair of them that live jollily. The remembrance of an happy ſtate makes us to be in a moſt grievous puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the abſence of thoſe delights we us'd our ſelves to, ſo galls us that it were better never to enjoy, or never to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them.</p>
               <p>What then upon this ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can a Chriſtian loſe that the Irreligious does not? It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid he has loſt all the pleaſures his Religion forbid him to enjoy, ſince 'tis evident this loſs is common to both, in that ſtate we conſider them. Or, to ſpeak more properly, the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29506:15"/>Irreligious is the only loſer, ſince the other cannot loſe thoſe pretended advantages he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver poſſeſt.</p>
               <p>However death raviſhes from the firſt all the vain felicity of his life. The Annihilation which he is ready to fall into, deprives him of the leaſt ſentiment of it; he is not nearer to happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs then the Chriſtian: ſince both being ſuppos'd to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilated, they loſe equally all the conſequences of being, as pleaſures, happineſs and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>This is the greateſt evil that can attend a Chriſtian ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that his Religion ſhould prove falſe, to loſe as much as the Irreligious does. But the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29506:16"/>Irreligious ſtands not upon ſo good terms; for what courſe ſoever things may take, if his opinion miſleads him not, he wins nothing; and if he comes to be deceiv'd his loſs muſt needs be infinite. It is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that he gets nothing for the future, ſince he expects to be annihilated, which deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſoul is the ruine of the hopes he could have enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd.</p>
               <p>But if he chances to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake in the Ideas of things, he has fram'd to himſelf; if he finds when his body is dead that his ſoul cannot dye; but falls into the hands of the living God; if there is after this life an eternal happineſs of which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29506:16"/>he is for ever depriv'd, and a place of unſpeakable torments to which he is condemn'd, who can apprehend the greatneſs of the loſs he ſuſtains, and expreſs his madneſs, to engage in a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the lamentable end whereof is ſo evident.</p>
               <p>And that which ſets off bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the diſadvantage of Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, is that the greateſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs an Irreligious man can hope for in this belief, is to come to that point a Chriſtian looks upon as his greateſt infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity. What is it that a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an fears moſt, but that after this life, there ſhould be no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of his ſufferings, no God, no Spirits, no Heaven, nor him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? And yet this is the grand
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29506:17"/>reward impiety can expect; it is brought ſo low as to receive as a reward what a Chriſtian looks on as a puniſhment; he muſt wiſh for nothing after his death but a general Annihila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the mouth of the deep ſhut up upon him; for if he chances when he goes out of the World to find either God or himſelf, 'tis impoſſible to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine a more miſerable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:29506:17"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>The Irreligious Man, and the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an compar'd in their lives.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre lies the ſtrength of the Irreligious, and it ſeems hard to convince him that he riſques more then a Chriſtian. A Chriſtian who ſticks religiouſly to his Law, muſt deny and offer himſelf a continual violence, he muſt ſet a Watch upon all his ſenſes to hinder them from betraying his heart; he muſt forgive his Enemies, oppoſe his own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and confine his paſſions to the ſevere limits of a Divine Law
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29506:18"/>Whereas the Irreligious lets his heart, his ſenſes, his paſſions run their full carreer, he checks none of his deſires; and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joys a felicity free from remorſe for the preſent, and not diſturb'd by the terrors of the time to come.</p>
               <p>And when we inforce this Maxim of prudence <hi>that in a doubtful caſe the ſureſt way muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be our choice;</hi> he oppoſes that other to it, <hi>that the certain is always to be prefer'd to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain;</hi> and the pleaſures of this life being certain, and the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of the next uncertain, it is a folly not to cleave to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent things out of fear of imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, or at leaſt of uncertain puniſhment.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:29506:18"/>
               <p>This is the Stumbling-block of the Irreligious, and the moſt ſpecious pretence of impiety, which may be ſo remov'd as to ſhew it ſhocks the very prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of natural reaſon.</p>
               <p n="1">1ſt. The ſuppoſition is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd, and Chriſtianity and Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion being both ſuppos'd as doubtful opinions, neither of which can be demonſtrated, how can they go under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of certainty or uncertainty?</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. Aſſurance being the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural effect of that which is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, as hope of that which is uncertain, it muſt be ſaid in their own opinion that we have a full and entire aſſurance of the goods of this life, ſince they are real and certain, and only
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29506:19"/>hope for thoſe of the other, ſince they are expected and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain. And ſo the queſtion is this, whether it be always wiſely done to prefer thoſe goods that we are ſure we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not miſs, to thoſe we have on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a probable ground to hope, how vaſt a difference ſoever may be found between them. The falſhood of this ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition is obvious, and might be a ſufficient anſwer. But becauſe it is not altogether ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act; that the queſtion may be ſtated in its natural terms, let us ſee what is wanting to to the certainty of the goods of this world, and what muſt be defalk'd from the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of thoſe of the next.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:29506:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> The longeſt life in its full extent ſeldom reaches above 80 years, nor conſequently the pleaſures that attend it. Since he loſes them, and ceaſes to be happy, who ceaſes to live.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly, All our life is not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of that happineſs. Old<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and Infancy muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded; nature muſt be endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a vigor Old-age has loſt, and Infancy has not yet attain'd: and ſo in comparing the goods of this life, to thoſe of the next, we muſt only reckon the time between theſe two ages. Staying upon theſe terms, the queſtion is this; whether a Wiſe man ought to prefer forty or fifty years of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant pleaſures to an eternity of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:29506:20"/>happineſs, which tho uncertain yet wants no rational grounds to be expected.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly, Health and Riches are abſolutely neceſſary to enjoy that happineſs which reſults from the poſſeſſion of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Nay this neceſſity is ſo abſolute that when ſeparated, they cannot make the Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous happy. Take from him his health, and he will be a walking diſeaſe; he will lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh and conſume himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Reſtore him his health, and rob him of his riches, he will be a Beggar brought to the greateſt want. What taſt can the delights of this life have for poor and ſickly people? They that need, are deſtitute of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29506:20"/>means of coming to, they that abound, and are ſick, of ſtrength and deſire to enjoy them.</p>
               <p>But Riches and Health, things ſo eſſential to his carnal felicity, are extreamly uncertain. No man can be ſecure of their poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion. That vaſt number of languiſhing people met withal every-where; Wounds, falls, Bankrupts, Sterilities, Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracks, Fires, Thefts, and a thouſand like misfortunes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray their inconſtancy, and teach us that nothing is ſo ruinous and uncertain as happineſs built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them.</p>
               <p n="4">4ly, Suppoſing that a vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous health, and a perfect plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all things ſhould conſpire to make you happy, how can
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29506:21"/>you be ſecure of your happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, if your life it ſelf is not ſecure?</p>
               <p>What is in the World more ſubject to alteration then our life? It depends upon the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of men, or all the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of Fortune. We may dye in all ages, at every time, in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very place; we cannot promiſe our ſelves one ſingle year, or one day, nay which is worſe, one ſingle hour. So many ſudden deaths ſet before our eyes are proofs againſt all exception, and what happens to ſome, threatens and is an argument of fear, for all. Our life is lent us by moments, and there is but that which is preſent we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Maſters of. We cannot be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29506:21"/>ſure of any goods but of thoſe only which this ſingle moment affords; all the others are only grounded upon a probable hope. And to this is reduc'd that certainty ſo much boaſted of, of the pleaſures of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life, to which this Maxim is ſtrangely miſapply'd, <hi>that we muſt leave the uncertain for the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> and ſo the queſtion is this; Whether any man of ſenſe can reſolve to give over the hopes of eternal happineſs for a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory one which is ſo often ruin'd by poverty and diſeaſes, and is ſecure of nothing but the moment of its enjoyment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:29506:22"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Limitation to be put to the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the promiſes of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is to be weigh'd on the other ſide that the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of everlaſting happineſs a Chriſtian propoſes to himſelf is not of ſo large an extent as one may imagine. For tho we condeſcend ſo far as to ſuppoſe that it cannot be made certain by any internal principles; yet it has all the external certainty a rational man can deſire.</p>
               <p n="1">1ſt, The univerſal conſent of Mankind in all times and places. The moſt Barbarous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29506:22"/>with the politeſt Nation, the <hi>Turk,</hi> and the <hi>Scythian,</hi> with the <hi>Roman</hi> and the <hi>Greek;</hi> and there is no irreligious perſon, but this propoſition muſt ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, that it is impoſſible to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſince the origination of mankind, any Nations or So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of men that ever made profeſſion of Irreligion; Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious having been lookt upon in all ages as monſters, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the enormity of their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but alſo for the ſmall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſtrangeneſs of their number.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. For what relates parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly to Chriſtianity, who can deny that it compaſſes the Irreligious with a cloud of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes? The blood of ſo many
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29506:23"/>thouſand Martyrs of all Ages, Sexes, Conditions, from the loweſt to the higheſt rank is an aſtoniſhing argument. And though ſome other Societies may challenge their Sufferers, yet the pains of our Martyrs are dignified by ſuch circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances as are to be found no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where elſe but under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</p>
               <p>And thus the Uncertainty of an eternal happineſs and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry muſt not be lookt on as thoſe things we uſually call uncertain, and admit of equal probability for their not-being, as for their being, but as a thing, which though not evident in it ſelf, yet has a ſtrong eternal cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:29506:23"/>
               <p>Then the queſtion propoſed is reſolved to this, Whether any rational man muſt prefer a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle moment of pleaſure he enjoyes, to the hopes of an everlaſting happineſs, which though not evident in it ſelf, yet is expected by all mankind, and ſo ſtrongly believed by Chriſtians that they have loſt for it, their quiet, their Eſtates, their Thrones, their Lives.</p>
               <p>Nor muſt the Irreligious ſay, That Chriſtian Religion is falſe, or impoſſible. For then he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues againſt himſelf; and is out of power of Claiming for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that the certain is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to the uncertain. If it be falſe or impoſſible, it is no more uncertain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:29506:24"/>
               <head>CHAP VI. <hi>Reſolution of the queſtion, Whether the certainty of the goods of this Life can overpower the uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of thoſe of the next. No Condition of men will aſſent to the choice of the Irreligious.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALL thoſe neceſſary limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being put on both ſides, it is eaſie to ſtate the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion in its natural terms. It runs thus, Whether a wiſe man ought to prefer advantages ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhort in their greateſt extent, interrupted by Diſeaſes, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd by thouſand unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble accidents, uncertain in their Duration, certain only for an
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29506:24"/>inſtant; whether he ought to prefer them to the hope of an Eternal happineſs, which ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny millions of men have dyed for; and expoſe himſelf to an eternal miſery which has the ſame probability? Whereas, without loſing that bleſſed hope, and risking ſo Dreadful a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, he may enjoy in an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent life, a part of thoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights he haunts after in a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful courſe.</p>
               <p>The ſingle propoſal of this queſtion is enough to have it reſolved. Is there upon earth any man ſo bewitcht, and ſo out of his wits, as to doubt one ſingle moment what muſt be his choice? Is it not a ſtupidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty equal to that of Beaſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29506:25"/>to prefer pleaſures at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with ſo many defects, to the rational hopes of eternal happineſs, becauſe theſe are preſent, and that is yet to come?</p>
               <p>But alas! Who ſhall make that impertinent choice? Men being different amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in age, condition, birth; the older they are, the proner they will be to catch at future happineſs; being ſo near their end that there remains for them but very little of the preſent. The ordinary ſort of people whoſe eſtate lies in their arms will think as old men. To them may be added all that live a laborious life, that is, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all mankind.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:29506:25"/>
               <p>I ask then an Irreligious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, what man is mad enough to ſide with him in his choice? If he is a Child, who knows yet nothing of another life, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little of this, he muſt not be proud of it. A Child knows but what he has tried, and he has tried but few things. He cannot therefore compare thoſe objects which affect his ſenſes with thoſe his underſtanding apprehends not. And his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though never ſo perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, will be ſtill that of a Child. If he is an old man in whom nature begins to decay, what would induce him to ſo ſtrange a choice? Does he think he ventures too much, when he parts with thoſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29506:26"/>he is not capable of, for a ſtate eternally happy, which though uncertain, yet is very probable? And would it not look as an incredible madneſs in him, that is dead to all the pleaſures of this life, ſhould he not renounce them, and chooſe thoſe of the next? If he is needy, and fickly how can he determine himſelf to it? I leave it to any mans conſideration, whether he that far from ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in wantonneſs has ſcarce time to live, had rather give over the hopes of eternal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs than to deprive himſelf of thoſe ſinful joyes, he never did, and never ſhall poſſeſs? And for them that lie under ſickneſs, let any wiſe man
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:29506:26"/>judge, whether he that has loſt the ſtrength both of his body and mind, and entertains no other commerce with men, but that which tends to his recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, is to prefer that little he has left him, to the probable hopes of an endleſs felicity.</p>
               <p>But why is the queſtion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to three, or four ſorts of men? Let that choice be offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to all Trades-men, Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Merchants, Souldiers, Seamen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Sure there is none ſo ſtupid as to prefer the hardſhips of their lives, to that eternity of happineſs Chriſtian Religion induces us to hope.</p>
               <p>Irreligion therefore cannot be the Religion of thoſe men. It can admit none for its Vota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29506:27"/>but young, rich, robuſt people, abundantly provided with all the eaſe, plenty and pleaſure this life can afford. No other condition is fit for it. Nay, they muſt be ſecure of perſevering in the ſhining flouriſhing ſtate they are: For ſhould any revolution ſpoile them of their Eſtates, any ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs enfeeble their bodies, or if they live to old age, their very choice which they look'd upon before as rational, will appear to them fooliſh and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant.</p>
               <p>Nay, they will not ſtay ſo long. Half a day is more than ſufficient to pull down the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent engine of their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. That which was true in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:29506:27"/>the morning, whilſt they had their health, will be falſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful, erroneous, ridicule in the evening if they are wounded or dangerouſly ſick. And though they ſeem then unwilling to alter their mind, eitherout of obſtinacy or ſhame: yet they cannot perſevere in it without proclaiming themſelves fools. There remaining to them only ſome moments of life depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of all pleaſure, and attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with torments, 'twere ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cule beyond what can be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined to prefer them, how pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and certain ſoever, to the hopes of eternity, how doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and diſtant ſoever it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:29506:28"/>
               <p>If then Religion is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to Irreligion when po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, ſickneſs, or old age full upon us; Is Irreligion to be preferred to Religion, when Youth, Eaſe, Plenty and Health leave nothing to our deſires to luſt after? Is not truth the ſame in our young as in our old dayes? Is there a Religion for the Rich, and another for the Poor? Certainly the truth of thoſe things, and much more that of God, depends not upon the alterations of our lives. It is ſtill the ſame notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the different diſpoſitions or opinions we are in.</p>
               <p>Nor can Irreligion ſhelter it ſelf in that vaſt number of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who by falling into ſin
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:29506:28"/>fer no leſs than they, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of tranſitory things to the promiſes of the Goſpel. Though it may be confeſt with grief, that all that has been ſaid againſt the irreligious, may in ſome ſenſe be applied to them, yet there is an infinite diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between them. When Chriſtians fix their heart on tranſitory things, they do it not in conſequence of their belief. They acknowledge that they act contrary to their Principles. They accuſe and condemn themſelves. If they ſin there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis not out of any Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious principle, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades them to prefer the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the future, and what they enjoy to what they hope. In
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:29506:29"/>their very ſins they believe ſtill the words of Chriſt, and truſt his Promiſes. But the corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of their Nature over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſways in them the Dictates of their Faith. An incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible weakneſs the firſt ſin left on them, renders them more eager after preſent things, though nothing comparable to the abſent. They are carried away through a violent paſſion which conceals the horror of ſin from the eyes of their ſouls, or truſts too much upon God's mercy.</p>
               <p>What can hence the Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious conclude? unleſs it were this, that humane nature is depraved, and men act againſt their own principles,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:29506:29"/>which ſhall be eaſily granted.</p>
               <p>But conſidering this maxim in it ſelf, and independently from the diſpoſitions of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular men; does any thing evince more palpably that it is falſe, than the ordinary courſe of the world?</p>
               <p>There is no man but leaves a thouſand times in his life the certain for the uncertain. A merchant ventures his mony which is certain againſt a very uncertain gain. A Conqueror ventures that peace he enjoyes at home, againſt a very doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſucceſs. A Plowman, a Souldier, a Pilot venture what they have againſt probable hopes of getting more. Nay upon this Maxim, <hi>Of leaving the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:29506:30"/>certain for the uncertain,</hi> turns all the commerce of mankind, ſince they diſturb their quiet, which is the thing they are moſt ſecure of, to come to what they pretend, which is full of uncertainty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:29506:30"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>The true Notion of this Maxim of St.</hi> Auſtin, Tene certum, Dimitte incertum.</head>
               <p>FRom all that has been ſaid, it is eaſie to conclude the falſhood of that maxim, that the certain is to be preferred to the uncertain. Now to judge how far it may be true, we need conſider but this: that when we are irreſolute, 'tis alwaies either upon the ends we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our ſelves, or the means to attain them. From whence theſe three Propoſitions fall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:29506:31"/>
               <p n="1">1ſt. When we are agreed upon the end, and only doubt which means are ſureſt to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it, 'tis the greateſt mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the world to leave the certain for the uncertain; to part from a way which leads infallibly to Heaven, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage in another which perhaps may end in Hell. And this Principle proclaims the mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the new Doctrine of Probability, that Monſter brought up by the Jeſuits for the total extinction of the ſmall remains of Chriſtianity in the world. For ſince all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans agree upon the end they aſpire to, and which is more upon the means Chriſt has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venus in the Goſpel, what is
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:29506:31"/>there more void of ſenſe than to leave them, for by-wayes, <hi>unknown, and untrodden paths.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2ly. When the end is not agreed upon, and that our mind is at a loſs, upon which to faſten it ſelf, it is to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned whether thoſe ends are equally advantagious to us; as whether the gain exceeds conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably the venture: and then the certain is infallibly to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to the uncertain. 'Twere indeed an inconceivable mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to venture an advantage quietly poſſeſt, againſt another of equal worth, but uncertain. All the reward of your labour, if you ſucceed, is to be in the ſame ſtate that you were in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and if you miſs, to loſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:29506:32"/>both what you poſſeſs and what you hope.</p>
               <p>This is the caſe of the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elliſts, who venture their lives that they may get a name. They loſe their life which is the greateſt of natural goods, to win an imaginary glory; which becomes after their death a real infamy to all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent ages.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly. If the end we pretend to are odds, and the good we hope conſiderably greater than that we poſſeſs already, the firſt though uncertain, is to be preferred to the other. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all things impartially weighed, the greatneſs of the good you hope, is a greater ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage than the certainty of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:29506:32"/>the ſmall good you poſſeſs. You hope indeed with uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, but that uncertainty is the foundation of your hope, and ſufficiently rewarded by the greatneſs of what you expect.</p>
               <p>'Tis upon that account that Merchants venture a little for a conſiderable gain though very doubtful. A Souldier and a Seaman expoſe their lives to the end that they may paſs the reſt of their daies more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably, though they cannot be ſecure of the length of their life, nor of a gain which a thouſand perils upon Sea and Land ſeem to obſtruct. They ſacrifice the preſent time to that which is to come: things that are certain to thoſe that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:29506:33"/>are doubtful, and look upon that comfortable living they promiſe themſelves one day as a greater happineſs than the quiet poſſeſſion of their life, with all the troubles and pains that attend it.</p>
               <p>Should the happineſs of the next life exceed this only of ſome Ages, or Degrees, there were ground enough to a wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to prefer the firſt to the ſecond. Nor is there any man of ſenſe, but would reſign up an age of ordinary happineſs, and ſuch as the world conceives it, upon hopes of a reign of a thouſand years, and a life infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely happy.</p>
               <p>But is there no proportion between theſe two ſorts of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:29506:33"/>Goods; if that maxim be falſe that the certain is to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the uncertain when the advantages are not equal: how much more when the one is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and the other infinite; the uncertain you expect infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely more durable and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, than the certain you ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>And this is the juſt idea we muſt form our ſelves of this and of the next life. What proportion is there between the pleaſures of this world and the happineſs of Heaven? What compariſon between joyes ſo limited in their Nature, in their Duration, in their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and thoſe unſpeakable ones, the eye has never ſeen
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:29506:34"/>becauſe they are not Colours, nor the Ear heard becauſe they are not Sounds,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt. Ep.</hi> 118.</note> nor have entred into the heart of man, becauſe it is too narrow for them? What equality can there be found between the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole earth it ſelf, and that of all the riches of God? Between the dark, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, paſſible ſtate of our bodys, and the bleſſed ſtate of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, and ſpirituality, wherein the reſurrection of Chriſt ſhall inſtate them? Certainly the Diſtance is greater than that of Atom to the Univerſe.</p>
               <p>And muſt the Irreligious be afraid of venturing that finite good, that Atom, that No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:29506:34"/>againſt an infinite Being? Muſt he not be aſhamed of claiming here the right of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring things that are certain, to them that are not? he who in the way, a hunting, on his tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, at play and in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce diſclaims it ſo openly? He ventures in all theſe things, with this difference, that there is ſtill ſome proportion in his riſque, and gain both of them being finite, whereas there is none between this life and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:29506:35"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Concluſion of this Diſcourſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LEt the Impious then extend ſo far as he pleaſes the greatneſs of his ſinful joyes. Let him live to the age of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſelem</hi> without the leaſt cloud or mixture of infelicity, yet he cannot deny that this long contexture of years and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is ſtill finite. He muſt needs conſeſs that an uncertain good is to be preferred to any other when it is infinite. The un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of it not debarring us from our hopes, and the laſt degree of hope of an infinite happineſs far ſurpaſſing the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:29506:35"/>of a tranſitory one. All the venture is to loſe thoſe tranſitory Goods, which loſs being already inevitable, cannot be parallel'd with an happineſs incapable of diminution.</p>
               <p>I ſee no anſwer to this, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept that eternal happineſs and miſery are Ideas ſubſiſting no where but in the fancies of Chriſtians, which is the more irrational, becauſe as long as they cannot convince their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of falſhood and impoſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, but ſtill doubts, and ſtill reaſons, all the foregoing ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cination remains in its entire force againſt him.</p>
               <p>This only may be added, that this is the conformity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Chriſtian and an Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:29506:36"/>man, that the firſt believes, and acts contrary to his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, and the ſecond doubts, and acts contrary to his doubts. Of the one it is too too manifeſt. The other talks as if he were certain, and thinks, and droops, without ever being able to fix himſelf. When he ſpeaks of Religion he is confident that it is altogether falſe, and impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; and when he reaſons, he finds himſelf expoſed to a bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs Sea of doubts and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainties.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="discourse">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:29506:36"/>
            <head>THE Second Diſcourſe. <hi>The removal of ſome Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections againſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is not intended here to prove the truth of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, this having been already done by great men, with a ſucceſs anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to their expectation; but only to remove ſome of the moſt ſubſtantial Objections of the Irreligious, whereby Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion is evinced to be at leaſt moſt probable. They
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:29506:37"/>may be reduc'd to theſe three heads. <hi>The ſeeming lowneſs of the myſteries Chriſtian Religion ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges us to believe. The incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſibility of our Doctrine. The impoſſibility of thoſe Miracles we look upon as the foundation of our Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:29506:37"/>
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The Lowneſs and Deſpicableneſs of our Myſteries anſwered.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis reproach is not peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar to the Irreligious. The <hi>Jews</hi> before them had lookt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the death of Chriſt as a ſtumbling block, and the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens as a fooliſhneſs. <hi>Marcio</hi> and <hi>Valentinus,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates it, did teach that Chriſt had aſſumed an imaginary bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and his Birth and Death were only illuſions put upon the eyes of the Spectators. <hi>Apel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> would have him covered with a real fleſh, but borrowed from the Stars, and not from
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:29506:38"/>the Bleſſed Virgin. Thus man would have ordered the grand myſterie of Incarnation, had he been Maſter of it. He would have left the bare diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to God; as if he could or ſhould do nothing elſe but what man is able to think.</p>
               <p>The occaſion of thoſe Dreams of the Hereticks, was that they believed Chriſt's hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliations unworthy of him, and the ground of the Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men is that they believe they are unworthy of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Both are as different in their conſequences as in their principles. The firſt conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that he had no real body, nor had really ſuffered. The ſecond from the birth and death
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:29506:38"/>of Chriſt inferred that he was no God. The aim of both is to ſeparate ſufferings from God, as things altogether irreconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable. The Irreligious deſtroy the Divinity of Chriſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his humiliations; The Hereticks deny his humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to preſerve his Divinity. Chriſtians unite them both in the perſon of Chriſt; acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging that though God, as his Father; yet he is become lower than the Angels, taking upon him our nature; and lower than men, ſuffering for them a moſt cruel and ſhameful death.</p>
               <p>Suppoſing then as a Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that Chriſt is God, it is no hard task to prove that his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliations
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:29506:39"/>are ſo far from ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the belief of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, that they enforce and ſupport it. Let them be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to any man of ſenſe, and he will conclude:</p>
               <p n="1">1ſt. That his humiliations can bring no alteration to his Divinity; God being wholly immutable and incapable of decay, to what ſtate ſoever he is pleaſed to deſcend. <hi>Periculum ſtatus ſui Deo nullum eſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertul. de carn. Chriſt.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2ly. That if he took upon him the vile and deſpicable form of a man, 'twas becauſe he would have it ſo. He could have come inveſted with all the majeſty expected from the Son of God. His reſurrection, his
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:29506:39"/>aſcenſion, his fitting at the right hand of his Father, are myſteries as full of Glory, as the others are of ſhame. He is inſtated by them in that ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did appearance the Irreligious and Jews would have him in at the beginning. So that his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliations cannot be attributed to any want of power.</p>
               <p>Nor dares the Irreligious deny theſe glorious Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; unleſs he reſolves to yield up thoſe he looks upon as ſo ſhameful. Knowing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of either of thoſe but from the relation of the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, he muſt equally receive, or reject the whole matter of fact.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:29506:40"/>
               <p n="3">3ly. That he did it becauſe he would do it, and that he would do it becauſe he loved us. <hi>He loved man in his miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and infirmities; and who can turn into a crime ſo ſtupendious, ſo miraculous a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tert ull. ib.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4ly. That nothing is really low or ſhameful but what bears the character of ſin. The Greatneſs of God ſhines in the number, order and motion of the Heavens. Nor does he fall from his Majeſty, when he applies his power to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the vileſt inſects. His providence maintains them; His immenſity renders him preſent in the horrideſt places. Nor did yet any man think all
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:29506:40"/>theſe things a ſhame and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to him. Yet almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God is as really in them after his manner, as Chriſt in his myſteries of Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:29506:41"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Chriſtian Religion obliges us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve impoſſibilities, and things beyond the reach of nature: An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat nothing is to be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved but what is ſeen is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous in the very doctrine of Irreligion, whoſe abetters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve many things they never ſaw. Who of them denies <hi>Antipodes,</hi> though they never were there? Who of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſes the teſtimony of facts related by prophane Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, becauſe they never ſaw the like? Who of them disbelieves many things he has been told,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:29506:41"/>becauſe ſome of them proved falſe, and makes his private opinion the rule of what is cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, and poſſible?</p>
               <p>But it is demonſtrable the Irreligious can deny none of thoſe miracles which are obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the Scripture. There are but two wayes of diſproving miracles. Firſt, ſhewing their impoſſibility. Secondly, Their want of Authority. It is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether out of their power to prove the firſt.</p>
               <p>A miracle is either impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as being beyond the force of nature. If he thinks them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible in that ſenſe, ſo far we agree. Or it is impoſſible to God, and this he cannot aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert according to his own prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:29506:42"/>Or impoſſible in it ſelf, and this cannot be made out, but by demonſtrating a real, certain, evident contradiction in them.</p>
               <p>And if we conſider things in themſelves, what impoſſibility is there, that a ſoul, and body, which were united a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould join again, and be in the ſame ſtate they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their ſeparation, if there is a power capable of uniting them? What contradiction is there that a blind man ſhould receive his ſight; a dumb man his ſpeech; a Paralytick his limbs? Nature doing it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with time and remedies, why cannot a ſuperiour power do it in a moment?</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:29506:42"/>
               <p>For the ſecond, <hi>viz.</hi> Want of authority, no Irreligious ſure will charge them with. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the integrity of them that tranſmitted them to us; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their principle that no lye was lawful, but that a lye in matter of Religion was dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable; they ſay nothing but what they have been eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of. Some of thoſe mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles have been believed for three thouſand years; and preſerved by a people that has built their Religion upon them. The reſt have been believed ſixteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years ſince, and contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the converſion of all the nations of the Earth. Their Preachers ſealed them with their blood; wrought the ſame,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:29506:43"/>if not greater, and induced by them an infinite number of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all Ages and Conditions to dye for the truth of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</p>
               <p>'Tis matter of fact that before Chriſtian Religion was brought into the world, all Nations, the Jews excepted, were Idolaters. It is another matter of fact, that thoſe Idolaters changed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and from Infidels became Chriſtians. And what greater proof than this can be required for the authority of miracles? how could ſuch a ſudden alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration be ſeen in the world without an infinite number of wonders which backt and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported the Goſpel? Were ſo many millions of men meer
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:29506:43"/>children, whoſe mind was alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at firſt ſight? Were they ſo ſtupid and ſimple as to receive any new Doctrine, without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment and upon truſt? Is not the Hiſtory full of the ſtrange exceſſes Nations ran to, to defend thoſe errors the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt would remove from them? Could they be overcome after ſo long, ſo ſtout a reſiſtance by any other force than that of miracles? Do not the violent and laſting perſecutions of the Primitive Church, evince that they were of a Religion contrary to ours? How could twelve Fiſhermen agree upon ſo ſtrange a reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as that of delivering lyes to all the world, and be ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:29506:44"/>as no torments could perſwade them to deſiſt from their fooliſh undertaking? How could ſo many Nations aſſent to lies, which procured nothing to their defenders but death and ſufferings? How could they venture their lives to maintain and tranſmit them to us by a conſtant and uninterrupted tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition? Certainly one ſhould convince us firſt, that all thoſe Nations were naturally mad, and apt to prefer a ſevere law which extends its empire to the very deſires of the heart, and has for its Promulgators men unknown and perſecuted every where, to their firſt Religion which put no limits to their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity. And before any body
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:29506:44"/>ſhould embrace Irreligion, the Irreligious is concerned to prove by ſolid arguments that thoſe changes are naturally poſſible; and the more becauſe they are ſo particular to Chriſtianity as to be found no-where elſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:29506:45"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The incomprehenſibility of things Chriſtian Religion obliges us to believe, anſwered. The injuſtice and abſurdity of that reproach.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Irreligious complains many points are propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to his belief which it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for him to underſtand; as if nothing was to be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved but what falls under his ſenſes. Which reproach may be reduced to theſe two Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions: <hi>That nothing is to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, but what may be comprehended,</hi> and <hi>that things are not when they are incomprehenſible.</hi> Then which two propoſitions nothing can
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:29506:45"/>be imagined more imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent.</p>
               <p>Beſides that thereby a weak, frail, blind man makes his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate underſtanding the rule of all things; is it not palpable that we cannot comprehend thoſe very things which are moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious? And thus muſt we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve nothing that we ſee, hear, touch, ſmell and taſt, ſince we cannot comprehend any of thoſe things; he being only ſaid to comprehend <hi>that can know the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret cauſes of thoſe effects which affect our ſenſes; make out the internal principles which compoſe all bodies, and tell us what are the differences that diſtinguiſh beings amongst themſelves;</hi> which no man living can do, not only in
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:29506:46"/>remote, but even in the moſt ordinary things.</p>
               <p>Nay the incomprehenſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our myſteries is ſo far from taking away any part of their credibility, that it renders them more credible. The moſt natural conſequence that can be drawn from the exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence of God, is that he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible. Were he not ſo, the concluſion is evident, <hi>therefore he is not.</hi> Suppoſing then that there is a God, he muſt be infinite and omnipotent. But were he comprehenſible, his infinity and omnipotence were meer contradictions. It is the eſſential character of his Nature, that neither his eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, nor great works can be
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:29506:46"/>know. Should I doubt of theſe two qualities Religion teaches me he has, the neareſt way to have it cleared up, would be to examine the effects attributed to him. If they did not ſurpaſs my underſtanding I ſhould ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and deny them. But were they incomprehenſible to any humane apprehenſion, it would be an infallible ſign of their certainty.</p>
               <p>I look then upon the works faith aſcribes to God. I read that he has made the world with nothing; that he has im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed in the Skies, and Stars, a motion, that would be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, were it not ſtopt by the ſame hand as formed it: that he has united without mixture
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:29506:47"/>or confuſion Divine nature to the Humane in the perſon of Chriſt: that this <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> raiſed himſelf from the dead, and will raiſe alſo all men: thoſe miracles ſurpaſſing infinitely the reach of my underſtanding, I conclude they become him who is omnipotent and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite.</p>
               <p>There is no anſwer can be given to this, except one ſhould prove that incomprehenſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is not the conſequence of an infinite being, which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly abſurd. What is then the ſhift the Irreligious recourſe to? He ſtares at the word <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible</hi> and concludes there is no God. That is, he makes uſe of the propriety of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:29506:47"/>a being to deſtroy the being it ſelf; he denies him by that which proves moſt convincing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that he is. He is incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible, therefore he is not. This is the height of abſurdity. I ſhould as well conclude that man is not rational, becauſe he reaſons, and found out Arts and Sciences.</p>
               <p>But incomprehenſibility be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing relative to our humane ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, whoſe bounds are too narrow to apprehend God, who does not ſee, that to reject the belief of his being, and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries upon his being incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible, is to make igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and darkneſs a ſhield againſt Religion. An abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty equal to that of him who
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:29506:48"/>would not believe the Sun ſhines at noon, becauſe his eyes are too weak to look upon him ſtedfaſtly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:29506:48"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>The Irreligious in his principles can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not avoid to believe incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible things.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is now an eaſie thing to ſee how unjuſtly the Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious refuſes to believe ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural things, who is forc't to admit of natural that are no leſs evident, and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible to him. And thus when he endeavors to anſwer the greateſt evidence according to his own princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, or elude miracles the fact whereof he cannot deny, he falls into ſuch abſurdities, as exact from him as hard a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:29506:49"/>as the faith of Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>He cannot but ſee that the world, and all the beings it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes, keep ſtill the ſame order. The viciſſitude of daies and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the conſtant ſucceſſion of generations whereby the world is preſerved, and renewed, is ſtill the ſame. The very firſt thoughts that ſuch a ſpectacle gives him is to know what has been, or will be its duration; That is, whether it had a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning or ſhall have an end.</p>
               <p>A Chriſtian faſtning his knowledge upon Scripture, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves that God created the world, and ſhall deſtroy it in that time only known to him. And when he has askt, how ſuch a thing would be done,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:29506:49"/>he acknowledges it is inconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, <hi>tota ratio fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti eſt potentia faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entis.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. Ep. ad Jan.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Irreligious of the other ſide not being able to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend how God could have fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſo many vaſt bodies with nothing, had rather believe that the world ever was, and will ever be as it is. And ſo to avoid the creation which he cannot conceive, he believes rather the eternity of the world which ſuppoſes it never was created.</p>
               <p>Now let any body compare theſe two beliefs. Is the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the world eaſier to comprehend than its creation? Is it harder to believe that God
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:29506:50"/>by his infinite power created all beings, than that they did alwaies ſubſiſt without either author or dependency? Is there light and conviction enough in the opinion of the eternity of the world, to venture upon its eternal torments which the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial of the creation engages us to? All the favour an Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man can expect, is that they are both incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. If we cannot know how one ſingle grain of Sand has been made of nothing; much leſs can we conceive a chain of Years, Ages and Generations, which being limited of one ſide, is ſo infinite of the other, that the firſt link is not to be found.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:29506:50"/>
               <p>Reaſon therefore being blind on both ſides, authority alone can incline our minds to one, or to the other. But in this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Chriſtian Religion claims all the advantage.</p>
               <p>The Doctrine of the creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world has been tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to us by <hi>Moſes,</hi> that is, by the ancienteſt of all Writers, as living not long after thoſe Patriarchs whoſe names came down to us. That tradition was preſerved amongſt the Jews; then amongſt the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians down to us, and will laſt to the end of the world. It was received by the Heathens them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Moſt of the Platoniſts underſtood their Maſter in that ſenſe, and they who did not,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:29506:51"/>but only believe that matter was eternal, did confeſs that the world in its being and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation depended from an eternal and independent cauſe. They admitted of the ancient Chaos wherein all the Elements had been mixt and confuſed; the ſeparation whereof they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the ſame agent who ordered them as we ſee.</p>
               <p>Some Philoſophers knowing nothing of it, brought up the eternity of the world, and that upon very weak conjectures. The Diſciples of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brac'd it rather, than confeſs it had been created. And inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, fires, plagues, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſportations of Nations, and above all the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of kings
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:29506:51"/>and the deep ignorance that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Idolatry defaced the very remains of that tradition. It was the conſtant opinion of ſome Nations that the world was eternal.</p>
               <p>Hence fair play was given to their pride that diſputed anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. They imagined that to be the ancienteſt, which gave them right to look upon the reſt as younger Brothers. The <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and the <hi>Ethiopians</hi> claimed that honour, and declared that they came immediately from the womb of the earth. And the <hi>Athenians</hi> took the proud ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>Chaldaeans</hi> and <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> carried their Diſpute to the very height. The firſt, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:29506:52"/>
                  <hi>Diodorus,</hi> and <hi>Tully,</hi> who laugh at both, ſaid that when <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great over-run <hi>Aſia,</hi> they had already appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves to the ſtudy of the Stars juſt four hundred ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty thouſand years. And not reckoning their years by the reign of their Kings, but divers periods, ſome of ſix thouſand, others of ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, the leaſt of ſixty years they made up their account. The <hi>Egyptians</hi> wanted no num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to outvie them. They found in their <hi>Archives,</hi> that ſince they had the name of <hi>Egyptians,</hi> the Stars had already compleated four times their great revolution, that is, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the ſame ſtate where
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:29506:52"/>they were when they began to move: which includes an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible number of years. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as proud of Aſtrology as the <hi>Caldaeans,</hi> they boaſted to have kept the <hi>Ephemerides</hi> of an infinite number of years, and the lives of their Kings all that time. An Author of theirs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates three branches of them. One of Gods, the other of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes, the third of men, who reigned an infinite number of ages. Nay they were ſo thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of antiquity as to ſay that <hi>Vulcan</hi> their firſt King reigned innumerable ages. But the <hi>Annals</hi> of his reign were loſt. The Sun ſucceeded to him as being his Son, and reigned ſix hundred thouſand, ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:29506:53"/>ſeventy four years.</p>
               <p>May it not be askt whether the brain of them that made ſuch reckoning, or of them that believed them was well ſettled? and yet this is the ground of the belief of the Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious. Thoſe Dreams are all the ſhelter they can find, if they go to prove the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the world by way of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
               <p>They agree therefore with Chriſtians in that they believe incomprehenſible things. But with this difference, that we believe only upon the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of God who has revealed them. We are perſwaded that his power goes farther than our apprehenſion. And that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:29506:53"/>within, and works with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out himſelf greater wonders than we are able to conceive. And as it is alwaies rational to truſt him who is infinitely wiſe, ſo reaſon it ſelf forces us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve things beyond reaſon.</p>
               <p>This impotency of concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the works of God is the only thing can make us happy. What ſort of God is this that can be included in the narrow minds of men? Certainly an object of this nature is a ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ground of felicity. And our hopes being inſeparable from our faith, his incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſibility is the greateſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of our ſouls.</p>
               <p>This Irreligious will admit of nothing but what his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:29506:54"/>or his experience make plain to him. When therefore they believe any thing they neither ſee nor apprehend; their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief is not grounded upon the certainty or evidence, but the intereſt they have in things. It is not the object that deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines and fixes their belief, but their heart and inclinarions. They believe that ſuch a thing is after ſuch a manner, becauſe they know it, and are ſatisfied, but becauſe they would have it ſo. Nay, they carry ſo far that abuſe of their reaſon, that when they cannot avoid to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve things morally incredible, they had rather believe them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible by their groſs abſurdity, than any divine grandure that lies in them.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:29506:54"/>
               <p>Theſe are the miſerable ſhifts of the Irreligious. But if they could ſtay there, and feed themſelves with the imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their hearts without any danger, we had nothing to ſay to them. All wiſe men would only think them out of their wits; and ſo far 'tis well 'tis no worſe. But to believe imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinencies and Chimera's with that danger, that if they mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, they ſhall fall into an eternal ſtate of miſery; 'tis a fury, a paſſion, an extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that wants a name, and can ſcarce be imagined.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:29506:55"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Abuſe the Irreligious makes againſt the Immortality of the ſoul of the conformity between man and beaſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is not intended here to prove the immortality of the ſoul; but only to ſhew how falſe and inconſiſtent are the principles of Irreligion. There is a vaſt conformity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween man and beaſt, in their ſenſes, in the multiplication of their kinds, their ſelf-preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, their paſſions, their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, their death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> From the mortality of the ſouls of beaſts the Irreligious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:29506:55"/>that of the ſoul of man, and thinks in that to judge ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the natural impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that form in his mind ſo many qualities, which being common to both make a ſort of <hi>prejuge</hi> againſt man.</p>
               <p>To evince how falſe is that ratiocination, it may ſuffice to prove that it is no leſs againſt, than for him. He concludes from that conformity, that as theſe of beaſts, ſo our ſouls die. Why not that theirs are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal as well as ours? The conformity being equal to both ſides, it muſt not be more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to one than to the other. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to all appearances, ſaies the Irreligious, Man, Beaſt, are altogether alike, in the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:29506:56"/>of dying, and in all the conſequences of death. But the whole beaſt dies body and ſoul, therefore the whole man dies ſo alſo.</p>
               <p>But the very ſelf ſame argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be thus as probably inverted. Beaſts and man are are alike in their death: But man dies in his body and not in his ſoul; therefore Beaſts do ſo too, and their ſouls are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal. Either of theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions muſt be equal to the Irreligious: ſince profeſſing to believe but what he knowes; he knowes, and can know the mortality of the ſouls of Beaſts no better than their immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:29506:56"/>
               <p>But Chriſtians, ſaies he, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the whole Beaſt dies. Which anſwer is the more abſurd becauſe he muſt not argue from what we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, but only from what falls under his ſenſes and experience, and what he muſt thence ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally conclude. But he ſees on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a Beaſt the death of the body. His eyes can go no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and concludes from that internal equality any thing for their ſoul. Or leaving the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer in its full latitude; 'tis in vain he makes uſe of our autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity concerning the deſtruction of the ſouls of beaſts, ſince we do it by reaſons which eſtabliſh the immortality of ours.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:29506:57"/>
               <p>But ſuppoſing with them and all the world beſides the morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the ſouls of Beaſts; all that can be concluded from their conformity with man, can only fall upon that wherein they are alike.</p>
               <p>There is in man that which is rational, and that which is ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal. Man is born, preſerves himſelf by nouriſhment, and his kind by generation. He is ſubject to the diſtempers of his body, the paſſions of his heart, the diſorders of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the neceſſity of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. All this is common to him, and the ſmalleſt Beaſts. Nay many of them out-do him in the perfection of his ſenſes. Their light is more piercing,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:29506:57"/>their hearing quicker, their ſmelling more refined. But all this is ſtill animal. All thoſe reſemblances exaggerated with the greateſt care, extend not to the rational, which is his grand difference. And ſo all that can be inferred hence is, that he dies in all that is beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in him: in his body; in his ſenſitive life; in all the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and operations that depend from corporeal Organs. But what is all this to the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of his ſoul, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon thoſe Organs, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his being, nor his ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
               <p>Who can hear without indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation this manner of arguing? Man is like beaſt in that which
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:29506:58"/>is common to both; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in all that is peculiar to him. Beaſts die in their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, in that ſenſitive life which conſtitute the beaſt, ſo does man; therefore he dies in that rational intellectual life which is proper to him. Man dies in his body, therefore in his ſoul. The Sun ſhines not when it is Ecclipſed; therefore he ſhines not at all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:29506:58"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Conformity between Man and Beaſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe conformity between man and beaſt is three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold; the firſt natural and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, the ſecond ſhameful, the third laborious.</p>
               <p>The firſt is the conſequence of an animal life. Man and beaſt agree in eating, drinking, ſleeping, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And although this ſtate be imperfect, as ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing many wants, yet there is neither ſhame nor pain for man. He does in that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt his reaſon, which is one part of his nature, and it is agreeable to the body
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:29506:59"/>which is the other. This con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity is inſeparable from man in this world. Nor is the ſtate of innocence it ſelf free from it.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and puniſhment of ſin. It conſiſts in the reign of our paſſions over us; the diſorders of body and ſenſes which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell againſt the law of the mind, and in all the ſhare luſt claims in the propagation of nature. This ſtate is natural to beaſts, and ſhameful to man, becauſe he is a ſtranger to it. 'Tis a ſhame for him, that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſhould command, when reaſon muſt give laws: that he ſhould not maſter his own ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: that he ſhould covet what
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:29506:59"/>is not his own; and love what he is convinced he ſhould not; nay ſometimes that which he would not love.</p>
               <p>Man is naturally no leſs ſtranger to the third, than to the ſecond: So many labours incident to his life, ſo many ſufferings and diſtempers that end but with him, cannot na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally fall upon an innocent creature. He muſt have been guilty to be afflicted.</p>
               <p>Nor can the Irreligious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance the ſufferings of beaſts, who are innocent after their manner. Why muſt man the moſt excellent creature upon earth, who was to command beaſts, be twice more miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than they. Firſt in the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:29506:60"/>multitude and diverſity of his pains, which come from the infimite number of his wants. Secondly, The quicker and more galling ſentiments of his pains. Beaſts are afflicted with no evil but the preſent. Man fears beſides, and foreſees the future. He who is condemned to die, dies a thouſand times before his execution. He feels infamy which outvies any grief. And by the help of memory is galled at the privation of a ſtate, the happineſs whereof he knowes moſt exactly, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires moſt earneſtly.</p>
               <p>Beaſts are incapable of any of thoſe pains, and nothing but a cauſe ſtranger to mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſuch as is ſin, could have
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:29506:60"/>ſubjected him to them. Sin alone could let into the world wars, diſtempers and death. And God could not puniſh the pride of man with greater ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, than to make him ſo like beaſts in ſenſible things, as they ſeem even to obſcure the immortality of his nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:29506:61"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>The difference between Man and Beaſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe chief difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Man and Beaſt, is reaſon; which comprehends memory of things that are paſt, and foreſight of thoſe that are to come.</p>
               <p>Hence ariſes ſpeech, which is not only proper to man, but a general means to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate thoughts, covering them with ſuch ſounds that men ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied their notions to. Speech is divided into all ſorts of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, nor is there any Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:29506:61"/>but makes uſe of it to keep up civil ſociety.</p>
               <p>Hence ariſe alſo Sciences, Arts, Commerce, Societies and Kingdoms.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is liberty, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference of doing and not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what he pleaſes: Whereas beaſts are determined in all their actions by a predominant inſtinct, they cannot reſiſt.</p>
               <p>Hence ariſe Laws to ſecure private men, and promote publick intereſt; which are grounded only upon liberty, there being no room for them in a nature determined to the ſame thing.</p>
               <p>Hence alſo ariſe vertues, which reſult from the good uſe of liberty and obedience to the Laws.</p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:29506:62"/>
               <p>Nay man is diſcernable by his vices. The love of Glory, and the deſire of Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſtinguiſhes us from beaſts, though our condition be not a jot the better for it; <hi>ſince all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires not overſwayed by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon render us more miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and miſery is never an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to raiſe our ſelves above any other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the queſtion is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beſides ſo many palpable differences, there is not yet ſome other inviſible that diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes man in his duration.
<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1ſt. To conſider the thing it ſelf, it is already very poſſible that amongſt ſo many external differences there is ſome inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal unknown to us. There is
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:29506:62"/>great probability that ſouls ſo contrary in all things are ſo too in their duration, and in their eſſence. How could man do things ſo far beyond the reach and capacity of beaſts, were not his nature nobler and perfecter than theirs. This ſuppoſition is very probable.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. If we ſurvey attentive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all the advantages of man above beaſts, they do all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply a natural tendency to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality.</p>
               <p>The nature of the ſoul is ſpiritual. This appears from her thoughts, which repreſent to her ſpiritual objects, and from general ideas from pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate images of things. But if the being of the ſoul be ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:29506:63"/>it is alſo immortal. Since a being totally indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from matter; is ſubject to no alteration.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly. If we examine reaſon, which is the character of the ſoul, it is bound within no compaſs of time. By the help of memory and foreſight no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is future or paſt to man. Memory recalls precedent ages: foreſight ſets before our eyes events that are to come. Reaſon enacts laws to order matters of men, if 'twere poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, for ever. Books ſhall teach poſterity as long as men live. Dying people intend by their laſt will to diſpoſe to all future ages of the goods that are in their power. There is
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:29506:63"/>no man but deſires eternal life and happineſs. None but fears infamy after his death. Nay, thoſe very men wiſh for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality who deſire their ſouls to be immortal.</p>
               <p>Are not theſe prejudices ſtrong enough to move any man? We have a clear notion of immortality. Our mind foreſees, our heart wiſhes for, every body aſpires to it. It is therefore at leaſt to be conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the number of poſſible things. And the contrary opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion cannot be received, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it brings along with it an evidence equal to that, of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſeen a ſoul annihilated, which never happened and never ſhall.</p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:29506:64"/>
               <p>Our eyes, ſaies the Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, are not witneſſes of the ſouls immortality. It is true. But are they of her deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Is not either of them equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unattainable to our ſenſes? What can then determine him rather to the belief of one, than of the other, ſince both are equally unknown to him?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:29506:64"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Some places of</hi> Eccleſiaſtes <hi>Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men make uſe of to prove the mortality of the ſoul, explained.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOthing ſurpriſes more than to ſee the Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous make uſe of a Book writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten againſt Irreligion. The <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> ſuppoſes every where exiſtence of God, and the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of man. He condemns the vanity of his deſires: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches him with ignorance in the works of God: draws a picture of the chief abuſes of all conditions: threatens all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners with the laſt judgement, and exhorts them to repent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:29506:65"/>death may overtake them.</p>
               <p>It is eaſie to ſee that all this is grounded upon immortality. If the ſoul does not out-live the body, it is needleſs to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade to actions of piety, which ſhould go unrewarded; and to deter us from crimes by the image of a judgement to come, which had nothing real in it. Certainly the deſign of <hi>Solomon</hi> being to lead us to God through the duties of a ſincere piety, this Book is directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the error of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the ſoul, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of her mortality being the foundation of all Religion.</p>
               <p>But had he eſtabliſhed it in any place, with what probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity could we make uſe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:29506:65"/>to deſtroy it? Unleſs we ſhould impute to the Wiſe man a ſhameful contradiction, and accuſe him to pull down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand what he intended to build after.</p>
               <p>The ſcope of the laſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter is to adviſe men to ſerve God from their Youth, and not put off their converſion to the laſt years of their life, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in repentance is ſo ſuſpicious. And having metaphorically de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the diſſolution of the body in theſe words: <hi>Ere the wheel be broken at the Ciſtern;</hi> he breaks off his metaphors, and ſaies plainly, <hi>Then ſhall the duſt return to the earth as it was, and the ſpirit ſhall return unto God who gave it.</hi> 12.6.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:29506:66"/>
               <p>Theſe words make out clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the immortality of the ſoul. If our ſpirit ſubſiſts not after the diſſolution of the body, how can it return to God? Can a ſpirit which is annihilated re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to his maker? And this ſeems to be inforced by the compariſon he makes of it to the duſt. For the duſt our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is made of, ſubſiſts really after the diſſolution of the whole.</p>
               <p>Nay, this duſt is immortal, no creature being able to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilate it; and matter remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing incorruptible to any natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral power. Therefore the duſt of our body ſubſiſting even af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our death, <hi>returning to the earth as it was,</hi> who doubts but
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:29506:66"/>our ſpirit <hi>returning to God who gave it,</hi> ſubſiſts after the ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. There is not the leaſt colour to attribute any other ſenſe to the Wiſe man. And we are naturally led to it by the juſtneſs of the compariſon between theſe two parts of our ſelves. <hi>The ſpirit ſhall return un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God who gave it, as the duſt ſhall return to the earth as it was.</hi> 'Tis the Wiſe-mans propoſition. But the duſt ſubſiſts even after the ſeparation, <hi>and returns really to the earth.</hi> Therefore the ſpirit returning to God who gave it, ſubſiſts really alſo.</p>
               <p>Nor is it an amazing thing that our ſoul ſhould be immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, ſince the duſt and earth ſhe animates is ſo too. And as
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:29506:67"/>death is not the annihilation of bodies, but their ſeparation from ſouls, and their diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into elements; ſo it is not the annihilation of the ſoul, but its ſeparation from the body, and reunion to God as her ſource.</p>
               <p>Indeed after ſo preciſe an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion of the immortality of the ſoul, any ingenious adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary will confeſs, that if ſome obſcure place occurs, it is a rule of common ſenſe to reduce it to the perſpicuity of theſe words.</p>
               <p>But what muſt one ſay if that very place the Irreligious uſurps againſt immortality ſhould ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it ſo plainly that it is meer nonſenſe out of that ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:29506:67"/>
               <p>The Wiſe-man ſaies, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving conſidered thoſe places where Judges ſit, he had ſeen wickedneſs in them, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety in their judgements, <hi>verſ.</hi> 16, 17. But that their verdicts ſhall be reviewed and reformed, <hi>When God ſhall judge the righteous and the wicked, for there is a time for every purpoſe, and for every work,</hi> that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be underſtood but of the laſt judgement, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſuppoſes before-hand the immortality of the ſoul.</p>
               <p>He adds, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18, 19. that <hi>he has ſaid in his heart concerning the ſons of men, that God might manifeſt them, and that they might ſee, that they themſelves are beaſts.</hi> 'Tis upon that account in the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:29506:68"/>Wiſe-mans opinion, <hi>that as one dies, ſo dies the other. Yea they have all one breath, ſo that a man has no preeminence upon a beaſt, for all is but vanity.</hi> And that they may be convinced of it, <hi>all go to one place, all are of the duſt, and turn to duſt again.</hi> This is ſo ſtrong a prejudice for ſtupid and carnal men, as it inclines them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that their condition is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly the ſame with that of beaſts. <hi>Who knoweth the ſpirit of man that goes upward, and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the beaſt that goes downward to the earth?</hi> 'Tis almoſt the ſame manner of ſpeaking as that which expreſſes ſo perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly the immortality of the ſoul, <hi>and the ſpirit ſhall return unto God who gave it.</hi> Which is the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:29506:68"/>Tame as if he had ſaid; in that deep ignorance of all things men are involved, there is not ſo much as one who knowes that which no body ſhould be a ſtranger to, being the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all Religion, that rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal ſouls are immortal, and that of the beaſts is not.</p>
               <p>It appears therefore clearer than light it ſelf, that the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man propoſes not this truth as doubtful, but as undoubtedly granted. Which is an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary manner of ſpeaking. When to exaggerate ſome points, men are engaged to know, one doubts whether they do know others which are more common? Is there an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, may one ſay, equal to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:29506:69"/>that of the Popiſh people in many places? They think it lawful to keep another mans goods, as long as the Law does not call them to an account; they blame no Oaths but perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Nay, who of them knowes whether there is three perſons in God, and two Natures in Chriſt?</p>
               <p>'Tis juſt the ſame trope the Wiſe-man ſpoke in. He is not uncertain whether the ſoul returns to God whence ſhe came, ſince he profeſſes it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly at the end of his Book; but he doubts whether amongſt the men of his time, any had light enough to diſcover this truth in the midſt of ſo much darkneſs.</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:29506:69"/>
               <p>If ſpeaking thus he ſeems to doubt of the ſouls immortality; he muſt have doubted alſo of the corruptibility of the ſouls of beaſts, his expreſſion reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing equally to both. <hi>Who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſpirit of man that goes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and the ſpirit of beaſts that go downward?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He muſt then mean this. Who knowes whether the ſpirit of man ſubſiſts after death, as it is uſually believed, and that of beaſts periſhes with the body? But is it a thing wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> could doubt of? Are men na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally inclined to believe ſouls of beaſts immortal? Could he ballance a moment to which he was to aſcribe immortality, mans or beaſt?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:29506:70"/>
               <head>CHAP. <hi>IX. A ſhort Analyſis of the Book of</hi> Eccleſiaſtes.</head>
               <p>THere is no conduct more liable to illuſions, than to pick up ſome places favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to ones opinion, without reflecting upon many others di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly oppoſite to it. Thus the Irreligious makes uſe of ſome places in the <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> which ſeem agreeable to his fancies, and leaves an hundred other which ſay the quite contrary.</p>
               <p>This artifice is eaſily over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown by this anſwer, either admit or deny them all, ſince all have the ſame authority.</p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:29506:70"/>
               <p>He alledges <hi>Solomon</hi> exhorts us to live pleaſantly: that he declares he ſaw nothing more advantageous under the Sun: and that it was the happineſs God had granted him, as if no other was to be expected. He underſtands all thoſe places of riot and ſenſual pleaſures, thus attributing to the wiſeſt of Kings to excite his Readers to debauchery, and all that can irritate the ſinfulleſt paſſions.</p>
               <p>Certainly one muſt needs have a ſtrangely low idea of things, to conceive no other joy but that which is carnal, and imagine <hi>Solomon</hi> exhorts us to fall into exceſs, he confeſſes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to have been guilty of. But one muſt needs be very blind,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:29506:71"/>who does not ſee, that he relates them only to condem them, and lay open their folly and emptineſs. To diſcern then what the Wiſe-man allowes, from the liberties the Irreligious claims, as if they were conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of his doctrine, it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed worth the while to end this diſcourſe by a ſhort analyſis of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes.</hi> The ſenſe of every particular place being to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by the deſign and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the whole Book, which chances to be the ſame, as of this Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>The general aim <hi>Solomon</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to himſelf, is to withdraw mans heart from the love of the world, the enjoyment of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and his eagerneſs for riches
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:29506:71"/>and tranſitory things, to the end that he may love, fear and ſerve God alone. 'Tis the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion he draws from the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he has ſpread through the whole book. <hi>Let us hear the concluſion of the whole matter. Fear God and keep his Commandments, for this is the whole duty of man. For God ſhall bring every word into judgement, with every ſecret thing, whether it be good or whether it be evil. c.</hi> 12.13, 14.</p>
               <p>The only ground he inſiſts upon to perſwade them, is that the world and all its atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance is vanity, abuſe, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and miſery for them that ſeek to be happy by it. Thus he begins his diſcourſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming, <hi>vanity of vanities, all
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:29506:72"/>is vanity.</hi> Then he gives an exact account of all theſe vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. He deſcribes exaggerates, and carries them ſo far as to render every one ſenſible of his own miſery. He preſcribes particular remedies for each of them. And becauſe his book is directed to great ſinners, he ſeems to compound with them; and to hinder them from fixing their love in the creatures; he allows them a moderate and lawful uſe of them.</p>
               <p>All theſe vanities may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to twenty three: ſome are drawn from the imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of creatures in themſelves; others from the ill uſe men make of them.</p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:29506:72"/>
               <p>The firſt is that all things under the Sun are tanſitory and ſubject to alteration; that all is obſcure and hard to be appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended; that there is nothing new, and the moſt glorious things are buried in oblivion as ſoon as they are gone. c. 1. v. 2, 11. That there are arguments to mortifie our inclination to preſent things, our curioſity for new diſcoveries, and above the thirſt of Glory and Fame ſo natural to all men.</p>
               <p>Vanity in learning, which requires ſo conſtant, and ſo hard a labour. 16, 18.</p>
               <p>Vanity in the pleaſures of this life, magnificence of build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and great number and variety of attendants. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 1, 11.</p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:29506:73"/>
               <p>Vanity in the ſublimeſt knowledge ſince it procures no advantage to the learned above the ignorant, both dying and being equally forgotten after their death. 12.17.</p>
               <p>Vanity in the hardſhips men undergo night and day, to heap up riches, not knowing whom they gather them for. That it is better to enjoy the fruit of his labours, than heap up ſtill, and ſtarve ones ſelf to inrich an unworthy heir. That this baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſoul is one of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt puniſhments of God, 16, 18, 26.</p>
               <p>Vanity in the changes and and cares of men, who are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to vary them at every moment. That how great and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:29506:73"/>ſatisfying ſoever be the works of God, yet mans heart wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill for an eternal and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable God, can find no reſt in them. So that the beſt way is to uſe them moderately, ſtill expecting greater things. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 1, 15.</p>
               <p>Vanity in the injuſt ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of judges, which the great Judge will diſannul. 16, 17.</p>
               <p>Vanity in that notorious equality between man and beaſt, in life, death and corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, ſo as to incline ſtupid man to doubt of their own ſouls immortality. 18, 22.</p>
               <p>Vanity in calumnies inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent people ſuffer, and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy to which they are expoſed who excel in any faculty. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 1, 16.</p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:29506:74"/>
               <p>Vanity in a mans continual toils who heaps up ſtill, though he has no heir, and intends to have none. 7, 12.</p>
               <p>Vanity in the revolution of ſtates, wherein from the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt rank one is often raiſed to the throne. 13, 16.</p>
               <p>Vanity in the quick decay of the greateſt fortunes after ſo many pains to be ſetled in them. 12, 19.</p>
               <p>Vanity in the greateſt riches, the owner whereof is ſnatcht away before he can enjoy them: that to judge that man by his own principles having put his happineſs in them, he muſt be accounted moſt unhappy. That a Child dying as ſoon as he is born it is not ſo much to be pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied. <hi>c.</hi> 6.18.</p>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:29506:74"/>
               <p>Vanity in the pompous fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals of the impious, and thoſe falſe commendations ſpent upon them in funeral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
               <p>Vanity in the multitude of objects which are ſo uncertain, as men know not very often which is moſt uſeful to them. <hi>c.</hi> 7.1, 18.</p>
               <p>Vanity in the long life of the impious, and precipitate end of the juſt. 16, 21.</p>
               <p>Vanity in women whoſe manners (in <hi>Solomon</hi>'s time) were ſo corrupted that he could find none good. 28, 30.</p>
               <p>Vanity in the proſperity of the impious, and perſecutions of the juſt. Whence the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man takes occaſion to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:29506:75"/>them who enjoy upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the plenty God has given them. 14, 15.</p>
               <p>Vanity in the laborious ſearch into the ſecrets of nature. 16, 17.</p>
               <p>Vanity in the deep igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance we are of our ſtate to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God; and of the great confidence of the impious, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe good and evil falls equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the juſt and unjuſt. <hi>c.</hi> 9.1, 22.</p>
               <p>Vanity in that fortune and hazard have a greater ſhare in riches than merit.</p>
               <p>Vanity in that the beſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels either are not hearkned to, or paſs unrewarded. 13, 18.</p>
               <p>Vanity in the unequal diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of charges and honours
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:29506:75"/>by the cheats put upon Princes. <hi>c.</hi> 10.1, 2, 5.</p>
               <p>The Wiſe man having end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the tenth Chapter with ſome moral maxims, takes up all the eleventh to commend diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of alms both to the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous and prodigal. Till at laſt he concludes his Book by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting men to return to God, before old age ſhould overtake them, as if he ſaid to them. If ſo many abuſes and vanities cannot unlooſe you from the world; let at laſt the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of old age, which being ſo near, will not permit you to enjoy it a long while, perſwade you to renounce thoſe goods willingly, which you muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly forſake. This is the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:29506:76"/>concluſion of all his arguments; the conſequence he draws from the conduct of the world he repreſented all a long in his Book; and the end of all is, that there is no ſolid happineſs here, but that it muſt be found in God.</p>
               <p>Hence it appears that <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> enumerates thoſe many va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities only to breed in us a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſte of the world. He reckons amongſt them all the pleaſures of his life, the magnificence of his buildings; the ſumptuoſity of entertainments, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his treaſures, the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of his attendants, and generally all the diverſions of a numerous and flouriſhing Court. He declares plainly,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:29506:76"/>
                  <hi>that having conſidered the works of his hands, all was but vanity, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, vexation of mind, and that there is under the Sun no ſolid and permanent happineſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus when he ſaies at the end of the ſecond Chapter, and in ſome other places, <hi>there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing better for man than that he ſhould eat and drink,</hi> it muſt be ſure underſtood of the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate enjoyment of the world, otherwiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> ſhould not be lookt upon as the wiſeſt, but maddeſt of men.</p>
               <p>But let it be far from us to think ſo unworthily of him whom God had endowed with divine wiſdom, to permit an harmleſs innocent joy, and a moderate uſe of riches equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:29506:77"/>diſtant from covetouſneſs and prodigality, is not to open a gap to all ſorts of ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſes.</p>
               <p>Men have been differently towards riches. There has been Saints who to give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wholly to the contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of heavenly things, did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely ſhake them off. Upright men diſpence them ſoberly. Sinners pervert them into an ill uſe, either ſquandring them ſhamefully, or keeping them out of a baſe covetouſneſs. 'Tis to them <hi>Solomon</hi> directs his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. It was eaſier to him to keep famous debauches within the bounds of lawful pleaſures, than to perſwade them they ought wholly to forſake them,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:29506:77"/>and paſs from one extream to the other. And to cure that baſeneſs of ſouls which ſcarce allows ſome people a ſober uſe of what they poſſeſs, his beſt way was to incite the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous to their moderate enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, he makes uſe alſo of ſome other conſideration to the ſame purpoſe. Sometimes he takes occaſion from the reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs curioſity wherewith ſome men ſearch into the ſecrets of nature, to tell them that a qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et and commodious life is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrable to that vanity. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he propoſes the neceſſity of dying incident to every bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and of ſuch influence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome, as it obſcures in their
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:29506:78"/>mind the immortality of their ſoul. Nothing being more powerful to ſtop the deſigns of an ambitious man, than to let him underſtand he muſt die, and has no advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage over the moſt deſpicaple beaſts.</p>
               <p>The ſmalleſt reflection up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe places, will perſwade any rational man <hi>Solomon</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not invite us to a ſinful joy, he condemns every where, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to an innocent cheerfulneſs inſeparable from a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Or if in the ſixth Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter he thinks him unhappy, who being left heir to a great eſtate cannot enjoy it, he ſpeaks ſtill ſuppoſing that mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diſpoſition, who having
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:29506:78"/>ſet all his happineſs in the goods of this life, is by his death ſpoiled of them, and expects no others in the next.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="discourse">
            <pb n="138" facs="tcp:29506:79"/>
            <head>THE Third Diſcourſe. <hi>Application of the two precedent Diſcourſes to the Irreligious.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>That the advantage being ſo great of the ſide of Chriſtian Religion. The Irreligious ought to rid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of all ſorts of prejudices, and the more, becauſe the diſorders of his life is the only ſource of his Irreligion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is rationally expected that no Irreligious man will hereafter think Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty falſe, becauſe all the articles
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:29506:79"/>of our faith are not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated as problems of Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry: they will confeſs it has at leaſt ſome degrees of proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility. Which being ſuppoſed, this propſition muſt take with any man of ſenſe, that it being probable Chriſtian Religion may be true, and if ſo, attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with eternal happineſs, or miſery; it concerns him to have it true by all means, and give over all prejudices againſt it.</p>
               <p>The Irreligious muſt then examine whether his love to Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religion is the effect of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of his mind, or of the corruption of his heart; Whether the falſhood, or the ſeverity of his maxims ſtaggers him. Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood indeed is offenſive to the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:29506:80"/>mind, but ſeverity only to the heart and fleſh; and no man, let him be never ſo little concerned for himſelf, will reject Religion upon that account. 'Twould be the greateſt paralogiſm in the world. <hi>Thus Religion is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, it forbids ſenſual pleaſures, therefore it is falſe.</hi> There may be pleaſures ſo ſinful as a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion may be true, and yet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid them.</p>
               <p>This ſearch into his own heart is the more neceſſary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe pleaſures, and paſſions, which may be called the reaſons of the heart, are the firmeſt grounds of Irreligion. It is worth our obſervation, and is no ſmall argument of its being falſe, that none ever fell into it who
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:29506:80"/>ſought for the truth with ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Study and ſobriety never led any man to it. It is not met withall in ones way. There muſt be wandrings to find it out; nor can it be ſo till after a laborious task to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and deprave his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
               <p>Nature cries, there is a God, and the world is the work of his hands. There is no people ſo barbarous but has heard that voice. As ſoon as we had the uſe of our reaſon, the Church took care to teach us; that our nature is depraved by ſin; that we are born children of wrath; baniſh our heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly country; that we ſtand in need of a Saviour who cures our
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:29506:81"/>wounds, reconciles us to God, and opens to us the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven; that Chriſt is that bleſſed redeemer; and that there is no ſalvation out of his Church.</p>
               <p>The Irreligious received thoſe inſtructions from his infancy. How came he to forget them ſo ſoon? By that ſad miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance did he engage in an opinion contrary to what he had learned at School, and condemned by all the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples he ſaw both publick and domeſtick.</p>
               <p>It is no hard matter to find out the cauſe of it. Diſorder and Libertiniſm brought him to it. The crimes of his youth have been as ſo many degrees
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:29506:81"/>that led him to the bottom of the abiſs. Ill companies ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the corruption of his heart infected and debauched him. The habit of riot and exceſs got ſuch holds on him, as it became a kind of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Yet he had preſerved light enough to ſee that his life, and the hopes of another could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver agree; and that if what Chriſtianity teaches of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere juſtice of God, of the immortality of our ſouls, and of the laſt judgement, was true, he was the moſt miſerable of men, amidſt his falſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights.</p>
               <p>There was therefore a choice to be made between a life ſo diſordered and a Religion ſo
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:29506:82"/>pure, both being irreconcilea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. But how could he break off the fetters of luſt armed and backed with a poſſeſſion of many years? The only thoughts of it made the whole heart rebel againſt the mind. Perhaps he did ſtrive to free himſelf from that oppreſſion, but fell lower than he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>He thought it therefore ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier to extinguiſh what faith and Religion was left him. He turned Almighty God out of the world. Or if he left him his being, 'twas upon conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that he ſhould have nothing to do with him in this life or in the next. He diſannulled the act of the laſt Judgement,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:29506:82"/>extinguiſhed the flames of Hell, called them tales and ſtories to fright Children, and to hinder miſery from ever falling upon him, annihilated himſelf after his death. He put a vail on his eyes only to peep on things. Then he ſaid confidently he ſaw nothing clearly, and there was no more ground to believe, than to disbelieve, or believe the contrary. In a word, he had rather run to thoſe exceſſes than refrain his paſſions.</p>
               <p>Yet if Irreligious men will give glory to truth, they muſt acknowledge that this was the way which led them to the pit. And what other arguments can they expect to be condemned by? Is that licentious life of
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:29506:83"/>theirs an argument againſt God and his Religion? Is the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel leſs true becauſe they are become ſlaves of their paſſions? Certainly they might degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate into the very ſtate of beaſts, truth would not be leſs unchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable. Before they had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged ſo deeply in ſin, when they lived an honeſt, Chriſtian life, there was a God, maker of Heaven and Earth, a Jeſus Chriſt who had redeemed us with his blood, their ſoul was immortal, and had they perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in thoſe commendable beginnings, Faith and Religion would never have decayed.</p>
               <p>But ſince they live diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all the world is altered. There is no God, no Chriſt, no
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:29506:83"/>Angels, no Devils, no ſouls. There is no Heaven to hope, no Hell to fear. All that has been annihilated in a moment, or become ſo obſcure, as not to be apprehended. But oh won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der! they begun to open their eyes only ſince they gave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the love of Creatures, whoſe natural effect is to blind. Now, are they not ſenſible of the inſufferable abſurdity of theſe pretences? And if they will anſwer ſincerely: what other proofs they need to be convinced that they are out of the way.</p>
               <p>But as their ſinful inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons darkned their underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they muſt never hope to ſee clear in the things of God
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:29506:84"/>till they are free from their ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very. Our heart being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſt with a violent paſſion for any object, is not calm and unconcerned enough to judge whether the Law which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns its exceſſes is juſt. He declares before hand againſt a Religion which bars him from his moſt tender deſires as an enemy to his quiet. And the mind covered with the miſt paſſion caſts over it, cannot weigh impartially the moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid reaſons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:29506:84"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Three Obſtacles the Irreligious muſt remove by three contrary diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF then the Irreligious ſeeks the truth with ſincerity, which the doctrine of Chriſt alone can lead us to, let him remove all the obſtacles that hinder him from being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded. They may be reduced to three; two of which are in him, and the laſt in God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
               <p>The firſt is his ſenſual pleaſures and paſſions, the ordinary cauſes of his ſins. The leaſt paſſion na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally obſtructs the mind, and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:29506:85"/>unfits it to pierce the cloud that lies over the truth. But ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al pleaſures are directly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the Goſpel of Chriſt; and 'twere a miracle if a ſoul charmed and poſſeſt with them could underſtand Religion.</p>
               <p>And ſo a ſober, innocent life free from paſſions and ſins is the firſt diſpoſition required of an Irreligious man. He muſt begin before-hand to live in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner anſwerable to the dignity of the law he examines. The King of Heaven as jealous of his authority as the Kings of the Earth, exacts from thoſe rebels that they ſhould put down their arms before he enters into any conditions of peace. This obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of theirs will be a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:29506:85"/>to faith, as faith is a neceſſary condition to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend our myſteries. The Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious would apprehend be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhould believe and obey: but he muſt do both before he can apprehend, <hi>Niſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>credideris non intelligetis.</hi> We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not know it better than from the author of our faith. The practice of his doctrine is the only way to know whether it comes from Heaven? He will will make an happy experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the truth of the words of the Prophet. <hi>The Law of the Lord is perfect, converting the ſoul. The teſtimony of the Lord is pure, making wiſe the ſimple. The ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of the Lord are right, rejoycing the heart. The commandment of
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:29506:86"/>the Lord is pure, enlightning the eyes. The fear of the Lord is clean, enduring for ever. The judgements of the Lord are true and righteous altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the Irreligious muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to examine the true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; otherwiſe he flatters him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in vain to have done his indeavours in that ſearch. As long as his heart is ſtained by the love of creatures, he has not gone the firſt ſtep. But ſeeking Religion without forſaking his vices, he united things that are irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable.</p>
               <p>The ſecond obſtacle the Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious meets in his waies, is a diſturbed buſie life, which ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to preſent things,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:29506:86"/>leaves him no time to think upon his true concerns. He is never at home. External ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects carry him from himſelf. And care, ſtudy and application being the only means that can help him in his ſearch, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them his undertaking will prove unſucceſsful. God is not to be found but in true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Church he has found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>is his dwelling place.</hi> There is from it but illuſions and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit. True Religion is very often covered with obſcurities, which incline proud men to think it falſe. God has hid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as it were with a cloud, that men might ſeek for him. He needs therefore all the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, care and induſtry he
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:29506:87"/>is capable of to ſee through it. If he ſucceeds or miſtakes, he is happy or miſerable for ever.</p>
               <p>The laſt obſtacle the Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous muſt overcome is the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God he has provok'd, who to be revenged of him, <hi>Spargit poenales caecitates ſuper illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citas cupiditates.</hi> The wrath of God is manifeſted in him by his indifference for any Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his invincible hatred to any thing that can diſturb the happy peace he enjoyes, and the diſpoſition he is in to live a pleaſant, eaſie, delicious life.</p>
               <p>From that deplorable ſtate of his flowes naturally a third con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition neceſſary to an Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man who begins to open his eyes, and that is, a violent
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:29506:87"/>grief. If it be true that there is a God, ſuch as Chriſtians adore, can there be a creature more an enemy to him, and conſequently more miſerable? Can a greater injury be done to almighty God, than to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude him from the number of Beings; contemn his Laws; laugh at his threatnings; reckon him a fancy which ſubſiſts only in a crackt brain; and live in a total independence from him.</p>
               <p>He cannot therefore be too much afflicted when he ſeeks for God; the loſs he makes of him being inſeparable from his own.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the obſtacles may deter him from Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Let his experience ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:29506:88"/>the ſanctitie and ſecurity of thoſe means. Let them try the truth of its maxims before they reject it, there being ſo nearly concerned that their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal happineſs lies at the ſtake. And <hi>what is a man profited if he ſhall gain the whole world and loſe his ſoul? and what ſhall he give in exchange for his ſoul,</hi> if ever he chance to loſe it?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:29506:88"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The Irreligious cannot be neuter in matters of Religion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe other part of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon being that Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion leads to eternal torments, is yet of nearer concern to Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious men. They may be apt to ſay that they renounce all other, if they can be ſecure of their preſent happineſs. That they have made choice of earth for their eternal manſion; and that this eternity of joyes ſo much talkt of could not make amends for their loſs. This ridiculous and fooliſh anſwer is
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:29506:89"/>made by ſome with great ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs. Preſent things have charms ſo ſtrong for them, that they cannot be torn from them. Their heart can love, and their mind ſee nothing elſe.</p>
               <p>Indeed their conduct would not be ſo ſtrange and unpardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, if there were but eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal happineſs to be won or loſt. They might renounce it nor think themſelves more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable for it. But everlaſting torments being into the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, that is the moſt lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table condition can be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; is not only uſeful, but of an indiſpenſable obligation to them to change their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief. There is no doubting and conſidering one ſingle mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:29506:89"/>'Tis fury, and Frenſie rather to be expoſed to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal torments than to embrace a party where there is no riſque at all.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, Irreligion only prefers annihilation to being and life: a nothing free from ſentiment and miſery to a life infinitely happy. And to give the beſt colour to their choice, they imagine that if they loſe it they are free from the ſmart of their loſs; ſince he can ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer nothing who is annihilated. But they will not ſee that in the uncertainty the queſtion was all along ſuppoſed to be, their pretended annihilation has its dangers and horrors too. If they chance not to be anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilated,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:29506:90"/>as it may, or may not be, they loſe not only a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed immortality, but fall into an everlaſting miſery. But if having performed all the duties of the Goſpel they are cheated of their hopes, they can be annihilated, which was their firſt choice. This ſeems clear beyond all expreſſion.</p>
               <p>Well, ſaies the Irreligious, I reject both immortality, and annihilation. I intend to be neither Chriſtian nor Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. I will keep a perfect neutrality. That cannot be. Of two oppoſite parties, you muſt fix upon one. To ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend is to declare your choice. Not to embrace the Doctrine of Chriſt, is to oppoſe him.
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:29506:90"/>Since 'tis no matter which way we go to work, whether by a direct and formal oppoſition of a contrary Sect, or by a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative unbelief; either of them ſpoiling him of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
               <p>Since then there is no medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um between theſe two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams, you muſt declare; But of which ſide? For that which is the ſureſt. You can do no leſs, if you have not loſt all ſenſe and care of your ſelf. In either of them there is ſomething to hope, or fear. The hope of Irreligion is anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilation; its fears eternal tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The hopes of Religion are eternal happineſs, its fears, annihilation. So as it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:29506:91"/>before the greateſt peril of Chriſtianity if it proves falſe, is the greateſt advantage of impiety if it proves true.</p>
               <p>Suppoſing then, as we have already done, both parties full of equal uncertainty, you ought ſtill to embrace Religion, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thereunto, if not by the certainty of the object, at leaſt by the neceſſity you are in determining between two objects, the one infinitely dreadful, the other infinitely advantagious. You muſt chuſe a Religion. You muſt avoid that which is attended by an unſpeakable miſery. Theſe two neceſſities are equal to any certainty.</p>
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:29506:91"/>
               <p>I am obliged, ſaies the Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, to be a Chriſtian to the double neceſſity I am put to of chooſing between Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Irreligion, and to avoid that of the two, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I may be loſt for ever. But I am nothing the better for it. My will may ſubmit, but my underſtanding is not convinced. I deſire, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not believe. 'Tis uſeful, 'tis neceſſary to believe, but that is nothing to me; ſince no man could paſs from doubt to perſwaſion upon ſuch ground as this; <hi>That whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is good and uſeful to believe is undoubtedly true.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Certainly what greater pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice can there be for the truth
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:29506:92"/>of doctrine which frees us from eternal torments, than the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of believing it. That delivery of ours being a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, real, effective good, all that can contribute efficaciouſly to it, muſt have the ſame qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications. And there is no Chimera, the belief whereof be neceſſary, or good, to avoid eternal miſery.</p>
               <p>It is therefore generally true, that whatever is good, or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to believe, is true and certain; ſince if it were not ſo, there would be no uſe or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of believing it. If tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling lies be ſometimes of any uſe, ſure believing of them is of none at all. Much leſs is there an obligation of being perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:29506:92"/>of them. And we may apply to falſhood what <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> ſaies of Sin: That they whoſe concern it is not to be miſtaken in matters of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are far from making it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be miſtaken. <hi>Nulla eſt neceſsitas peccandi iis quibus una eſt neceſsitas non peccandi.</hi> But the Irreligious acknowledge it good and neceſſary to believe Chriſtian Religion, that he may avoid eternal damnation; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he muſt conclude it true, and embrace it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:29506:93"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>The leaſt degree of probability Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion has above Irreligion, is enough to bring the Irreligious to a very probable opinion, and from opinion to faith.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SUppoſing Religion true and certain in it ſelf, it is not ſo to me, ſaies the Irreligious, who ſeeing nothing in it but uncertain, or at moſt proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Faith implies an aſſent to what you believe as to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and not a probable thing. How therefore can I believe any Religion as undoubted which is ſtill uncertain to me.</p>
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:29506:93"/>
               <p>This indeed cannot be as long as you have no greater light. But till it increaſes and flames to a higher degree, do now what lies in your power. You confeſs Chriſtianity is a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more probable than Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. That can hinder you then to embrace the moſt probable party, and ſpecially when it ſecures your eternity, reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and all other advantages. Muſt you be divided and rack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by different paſſions, and complain at the ſame time of the neceſſity and impoſſibility of believing? And why will you deny your ſelf in this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, that which you do in all others, that is, to follow the moſt probable opinion? Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:29506:94"/>was no leſs uncertain to you at that very time you lookt upon it, as more probable than Chriſtianity. Yet its uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty did not fright you from running into it. The liberty and independency it promiſed made you reſign up all your doubts. Why then, the one giving you ſo great hopes do you refuſe to do for it what you do for the other.</p>
               <p>Perhaps you deny it to be more probable. Well, let it be ſo. The moſt you can do for Irreligion is to doubt. Maintain as long as you pleaſe the eternity of the World, and the mortality of the ſoul. Put your ſentiments in their moſt favourable light, you can never
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:29506:94"/>demonſtrate and free them from doubts. After all your endeavours they will be ſtill opinions, and nothing but opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. But if you doubt of them in the leaſt, you ought to forſake them. It being an hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid madneſs to venture your ſalvation upon an uncertain opinion. <hi>Ipſo facto,</hi> that it is an opinion it may be falſe; and if it be ſo, you ruine your ſelf for ever. In a concern as important as eternity is, you muſt rely upon dogms which cannot miſlead you.</p>
               <p>But till you conceive how far Chriſtianity is from miſlead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you, ſubmit to it. That ſtedfaſt diſpoſition of mind to believe comes from the will;
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:29506:95"/>and if this be determined, the other will quickly be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded. Faith muſt not depend upon the relation of ſenſes, or the evidence of reaſon, but its own determination. You are not concerned to know, but to believe. Science may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge demonſtrations, but the glory of faith is to ſubmit to Gods authority. Though its ſeat be in the mind, yet it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends almoſt totally from the will: which induced St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> to ſay, that it depends from hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane liberty to believe or not believe.</p>
               <p>If ſome want penetration and light, none wants a good will. Nothing elſe is required to believe. Almighty God ſo
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:29506:95"/>tempered our faith, as to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion it to all ſorts of trains, becauſe being abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſalvation, and the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netration of men ſo different; had it depended from their parts the unlearned would have been excluded from it. But now the Ignorant are even with the greateſt Doctors. Thus it is eaſie to paſs from uncertainty to certainty, forcing our underſtanding to believe. Notwithſtanding all its relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctances; and reducing uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty to inevidence which is the character of Faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:29506:96"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>The Irreligious of education, if there is any, may be convinced of the truth of Chriſtianity, by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and miracles. The Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious of profeſsion muſt ſupply his want of evidence by a ſincere hearty will.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Do not know what can be oppoſed to thoſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples except one ſhould ſay that faith depends not immediately from the will, becauſe the will does not believe by it ſelf, but only determines the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to believe. But that determination ſtill preſuppoſes a conviction; the empire of the
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:29506:96"/>will being not ſo great as to ſway the underſtanding, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out at leaſt a ſeeming reaſon to ſatisfie it.</p>
               <p>This Objection might be of ſome weight, propoſed by an Irreligious man of education al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unacquainted with Chriſtianity. Then I would prove the exiſtence of God by the teſtimonies he gave of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the Scripture, and the Scripture by thoſe infinite won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders he wrought by <hi>Moſes,</hi> Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtles converted the world with arguments of this nature. Nations aſtoniſhed at the ſight of dead men riſing from their graves, could not doubt whether the power
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:29506:97"/>which exceeded ſo much that of nature, did really exiſt. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles made it viſible to their eyes; and this was the object to which their will applied their underſtanding, to the end it might be ſubject to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of faith.</p>
               <p>Nor has that ſort of Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men leſs ground to believe them, than all the Nations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by the Apoſtles. They muſt look upon thoſe miracles as if they had been wrought before their own eyes. They have in them the ſame power of conviction as they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and prove no leſs againſt them than they did againſt the Heathens. The differences of time take nothing from proofs
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:29506:97"/>which conſiſts in matters of fact. Miracles may paſs, but the truth of a fact is unchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable. It out-laſts them; and as long as it is true that Chriſt and his Servants wrought mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles to prove his divinity, they muſt ſeem to any ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal man invincible arguments.</p>
               <p>Suppoſing then that any man born Irreligious, ſhould deſire light to fire his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding upon, that he might believe; he ſhould ſeek no where for it but in the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of God who has ſpoken in the Scriptures, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed the Scriptures by mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. When God ſpeaks to us, his words are infallible, his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:29506:98"/>ſoveraign; our ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion bears no limitations: and the diſpute being reduced to matter of fact, any ingenuous ſouls would be eaſily ſatisfied. But there is no ſuch Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of education, all men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought up in ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion or other. The Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious of our times are ſo of profeſſion, decaied Chriſtians, concealed Apoſtates, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been brought up in the principles of Chriſtianity, were carried to Irreligion either by corrupted companies, bad books, and above all, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious inclination to riot and exceſſes. They want no light to believe the ſymbol of the
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:29506:98"/>Apoſtles. They need but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what they had been taught before their depravati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and refreſh thoſe Ideas ſin has ſo entirely defaced in them.</p>
               <p>They pretend they cannot believe, becauſe they do not ſee things with their own eyes.</p>
               <p>But there is a vaſt difference between not believing a thing, becauſe we have proofs of its falſhood, and not believing it becauſe we want ſufficient ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of its truth. The underſtanding may be more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ſubdued in the ſecond ſenſe than in the firſt; and the will ſwaied by the authority of the
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:29506:99"/>ſpeaker may ſupply the want of Reaſon.</p>
               <p>This inſufficiency or rather inevidence of proofs is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foundation of their incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. But alas, how ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and irrational? How won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful is the confidence of men who complain of the inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of proofs to believe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, whereas they have the ſame inſufficiency in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Irreligion. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times did paſſion or the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of their Teachers ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply their want of reaſon? Did they not produce ſo many acts of faith as there are incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible conſequences in the worlds eternity? Why do they
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:29506:99"/>refuſe to do the ſame now, and rely upon an authority conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable by an infinite number of miracles.</p>
               <p>They grant no more in that, but what is required of them either in ſciences, or in the commerce of humane life. They are concerning the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of God as an apprentice totally unacquainted with the principles, and terms of the art he learns. But there is no prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple apprentice, as the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher and experience teach us, but muſt believe what he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not apprehend. The blind belief he gives to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters directions, is the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all the perfection he can
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:29506:100"/>come to in his Art. The firſt elements of every Science can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be proved; and ſuppoſing they could, an apprentice is not able to underſtand them. His beſt is to receive them with an entire acquieſcence of mind.</p>
               <p>Why then do not the Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious in matters ſo dark as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is, imitate Apprentices in the firſt rudiments which are given them, or remember what they did themſelves when they firſt learned any thing? Are they more knowing in the deep myſteries of Chriſtianity, than they were in Geometry and Muſick. They aſſented blindſold to him who taught them to play upon the Lute;
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:29506:100"/>and they will not be aſhamed to exact from God demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for every Article of his Doctrine. Certainly Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on carries men to ſtrange extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. Is it poſſible they ſhould not ſee, that their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon muſt the more ſubmit to Gods Authority, becauſe thoſe myſteries he reveals unto us are infinitely more diſproportion'd to our ſenſes, than all Arts and Sciences in the world.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:29506:101"/>
            <head>Books to be ſold by <hi>Henry Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke,</hi> at the <hi>Red-Lion,</hi> in <hi>St. Pauls Church-yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>AGeographical deſcription of the four parts of the World, taken from the Notes and Works of the famous <hi>Monſieur Sanſon,</hi> by <hi>Richard Blome. fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Britania,</hi> or a Geographical De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Kingdoms of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> By <hi>Richard Blome. fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scapuli Lexicon.</hi> 10 FE 60 <hi>fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Curcellaei Opera. fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clarks</hi> Martyrology. <hi>fol.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bocharti Geographia ſacra. quart.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Glaſſii Philogia ſacra. quart.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dallaeus de uſu Patrum. quart.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cluverii Geographia. quart.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pharmacopoea Auguſtina. quart.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Diemerbroeck Anatomia. quart.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bartholini Anatomia. oct.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Schulteti Chyrurgia. oct.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Graaf Opera Medica. oct.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:29506:101"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Polidor Virgil Hiſt. Angliae. oct.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sermons Preach'd upon ſeveral oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, by <hi>John Tillotſon;</hi> D.D. Dean of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> Preacher to the honourable ſociety of <hi>Lincolns-Inn,</hi> and one of his Majeſties Chaplains in Ordinary. in two vol. <hi>oct.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The new Politick Lights of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern <hi>Romes</hi> Church govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or the new Goſpel accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Cardinal <hi>Palavicini</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed by him in his Hiſtory of the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rapini Opera. duodec.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Floſculi Hiſtorici. duodec.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fromman de Haemorr hoidibus. duod.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
